<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator>
  
  
  <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" />
  <updated>2025-06-23T19:51:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/</id>

  
    <title type="html">cariad.keigher.ca</title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Personal website and journal for Cariad Heather Keigher.</subtitle>
  

  
    <author>
        <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
      
      
    </author>
  

  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">2024, AI, and my side in the Butlerian Jihad</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/12/31/2024-ai-and-my-side-in-the-butlerian-jihad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2024, AI, and my side in the Butlerian Jihad" />
      
      <published>2024-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/12/31/2024--ai--and-my-side-in-the-butlerian-jihad</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/12/31/2024-ai-and-my-side-in-the-butlerian-jihad/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0vChTdqoDivbqEG5__1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depiction of the Butlerian Jihad from the books&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, my friend asked me to come over to her place to watch Dune Part One so she could the next day drag me to see Part Two in cinema. After that weekend, I gained a new set of worlds to explore: a universe once tainted by artificial intelligence but no longer thanks to a war with “&lt;a href=&quot;https://breezewiki.com/dune/wiki/Thinking_Machines&quot;&gt;thinking machines&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t my first experience with Dune, as I had at one point in my past watched the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dune_%281984_film%29&quot;&gt;David Lynch rendition&lt;/a&gt;, which came out the year I was born. However, the Denis Villeneuve version captured my attention due to its non-goofy approach to the story, and as a consequence I now find myself reading through the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One plot device of the (known) universe in Frank Herbert’s Dune is the lack of anything resembling a computer as we know it. Approximately ten thousand years before protagonist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Atreides&quot;&gt;Paul Atreides&lt;/a&gt; appearance in the story, the established royal houses were engaged in a war — dubbed the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://breezewiki.com/dune/wiki/Butlerian_Jihad&quot;&gt;Butlerian Jihad&lt;/a&gt;” — with thinking machines where humanity was victorious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0Qbo4gkyFYhTL6MqV_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thufir Hawat, a mentat as depicted in Dune (2021), played by Stephen McKinley&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory led to anything resembling a thinking machine considered as forbidden technology and instead led to humanity being dependent on but not limited to &lt;a href=&quot;https://breezewiki.com/dune/wiki/Mentat&quot;&gt;mentats&lt;/a&gt; (human computers basically), analogue technology, and genetic modification including eugenics (unfortunate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the real world of 2024, we don’t have to worry about computers having sentience and we never will in 2025, 2026, 2032, or 2038 — check in with me in 2039 for an update. &lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/openai-claims-its-new-model-reached-human-level-on-a-test-for-general-intelligence-what-does-that-mean-2000543834&quot;&gt;The suggestion that it will achieve artificial general intelligence&lt;/a&gt; (AGI) any time soon is absolute nonsense — the power requirements that AI-championing OpenAI is desiring &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/openai-reportedly-wants-build-5-115944436.html?guccounter=1&amp;amp;guce_referrer=aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuZ29vZ2xlLmNvbS8&amp;amp;guce_referrer_sig=AQAAAKGpMqYtIi0gew2IJPTVRrBWdZuBooCyleaDSdj3BwoDaivqVu2AxLMjfVv-8v9nG8MzT-i9dp8U77u8pJpRpHyLFXdHFX88H3vSQRIkoHjxzLIvReCvgncpICZnvN9EzSiaDlwJsIFLp-TdP1HWEUaMUGR7BIql1DTJeTQS8tdQ&quot;&gt;is the equivalent to the output of some countries&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/a-cubic-millimeter-of-a-human-brain-has-been-mapped-in-spectacular-detail/&quot;&gt;to map one cubic millimetre of the human brain required 1.4 petabytes of storage&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that to do its entirety, based on its average &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/how-big-is-the-brain-2794888&quot;&gt;size&lt;/a&gt; of 2,174,340 mm², you’d need 3,044,076 petabytes of storage. If you convert that to zettabytes, you’d end up with about 3, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://rivery.io/blog/big-data-statistics-how-much-data-is-there-in-the-world/&quot;&gt;about 2% of what is suggested as the entire Internet’s total storage capability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for one human brain. The entire Internet infrastructure is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thundersaidenergy.com/downloads/internet-energy-consumpion-data-models-forecasts/#:~:text=Our%20best%20estimate%20is%20that,2.5%25%20of%20all%20global%20electricity.&quot;&gt;suggested to consume about 800 TWh of electricity&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that to simulate this one human brain, you’d need 16 TWh just for storage — this is enough to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_electricity_production&quot;&gt;power all of Cuba&lt;/a&gt; just to put it all into context and we’re not even considering all of the other technicals we’d need to examine to pull it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1gaZdChB_XbH-9wsh_2lYSA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 640 grams each, you’d have 64,000,000 KG of these bad boys floating around for just one brain, putting them all at around 20% the total weight of the Empire State Building&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot map the entire brain without having to have nearly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.westerndigital.com/products/internal-drives/data-center-drives/ultrastar-dc-hc690-hdd?sku=WSH723220AL4201&quot;&gt;100 million of these hard drives&lt;/a&gt; spinning at any given time (imagine the failure rate you’d have to contend with) and yet we’re expected to believe arrogant pricks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam_Altman&quot;&gt;Sam Altman&lt;/a&gt; have any clue about what its usefulness is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we play into the fool’s statement that we only use 10% of our brains (this is untrue), we’d still need just over 1 TWh for storage for a human brain. Why are we suggesting that we go and speed up climate change in favour of a machine that relies on a garbage in garbage out philosophy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I became aware that I was put on someone’s list as “someone who doesn’t get AI/NFTs/crypto” — here’s the thing: I do understand it, but what I don’t get is why do these types of people who champion these fads never take a step back to understand them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a decade and a half experience with computer security and have seen so much change, but what hasn’t changed is the creature in front of the display. Humans are complex creatures; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consciousness#Scientific_study&quot;&gt;we don’t understand why we have consciousness&lt;/a&gt; and yet we have clowns in the world who suggest we can replicate some or all of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0Sl7c2Aacvr2G8oyM_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum computers probably won’t help either here — if they even ever work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of classical computers with their binary states achieving the intelligence of a human brain is short-sighted — the idiocy I already am making an argument for here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thousand lines of code is more than enough to power a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model&quot;&gt;large language model&lt;/a&gt;, which forms the basis for the AI software we see commonly today, but to suggest that is enough in contrast to the billions of years of evolution that led to our species being here today is pure hubris and will lead to us hoisting ourselves by our own petard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the Butlerian Jihad were to start today, I know which side I’d find myself on. Stop boiling the damn ocean to make soulless art, worthless and insecure code, and education materials of which are lacking in facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a brain; use it, exercise it, and find what you’re actually capable of.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Depiction of the Butlerian Jihad from the books Earlier this year, my friend asked me to come over to her place to watch Dune Part One so she could the next day drag me to see Part Two in cinema. After that weekend, I gained a new set of worlds to explore: a universe once tainted by artificial intelligence but no longer thanks to a war with “thinking machines”. This wasn’t my first experience with Dune, as I had at one point in my past watched the David Lynch rendition, which came out the year I was born. However, the Denis Villeneuve version captured my attention due to its non-goofy approach to the story, and as a consequence I now find myself reading through the books. One plot device of the (known) universe in Frank Herbert’s Dune is the lack of anything resembling a computer as we know it. Approximately ten thousand years before protagonist Paul Atreides appearance in the story, the established royal houses were engaged in a war — dubbed the “Butlerian Jihad” — with thinking machines where humanity was victorious. Thufir Hawat, a mentat as depicted in Dune (2021), played by Stephen McKinley This victory led to anything resembling a thinking machine considered as forbidden technology and instead led to humanity being dependent on but not limited to mentats (human computers basically), analogue technology, and genetic modification including eugenics (unfortunate). In the real world of 2024, we don’t have to worry about computers having sentience and we never will in 2025, 2026, 2032, or 2038 — check in with me in 2039 for an update. The suggestion that it will achieve artificial general intelligence (AGI) any time soon is absolute nonsense — the power requirements that AI-championing OpenAI is desiring is the equivalent to the output of some countries. Just to map one cubic millimetre of the human brain required 1.4 petabytes of storage, meaning that to do its entirety, based on its average size of 2,174,340 mm², you’d need 3,044,076 petabytes of storage. If you convert that to zettabytes, you’d end up with about 3, which about 2% of what is suggested as the entire Internet’s total storage capability. This is for one human brain. The entire Internet infrastructure is suggested to consume about 800 TWh of electricity, meaning that to simulate this one human brain, you’d need 16 TWh just for storage — this is enough to power all of Cuba just to put it all into context and we’re not even considering all of the other technicals we’d need to examine to pull it off. At 640 grams each, you’d have 64,000,000 KG of these bad boys floating around for just one brain, putting them all at around 20% the total weight of the Empire State Building We cannot map the entire brain without having to have nearly 100 million of these hard drives spinning at any given time (imagine the failure rate you’d have to contend with) and yet we’re expected to believe arrogant pricks like Sam Altman have any clue about what its usefulness is? Even if we play into the fool’s statement that we only use 10% of our brains (this is untrue), we’d still need just over 1 TWh for storage for a human brain. Why are we suggesting that we go and speed up climate change in favour of a machine that relies on a garbage in garbage out philosophy? Recently, I became aware that I was put on someone’s list as “someone who doesn’t get AI/NFTs/crypto” — here’s the thing: I do understand it, but what I don’t get is why do these types of people who champion these fads never take a step back to understand them? I have a decade and a half experience with computer security and have seen so much change, but what hasn’t changed is the creature in front of the display. Humans are complex creatures; we don’t understand why we have consciousness and yet we have clowns in the world who suggest we can replicate some or all of it? Quantum computers probably won’t help either here — if they even ever work. The idea of classical computers with their binary states achieving the intelligence of a human brain is short-sighted — the idiocy I already am making an argument for here. A thousand lines of code is more than enough to power a large language model, which forms the basis for the AI software we see commonly today, but to suggest that is enough in contrast to the billions of years of evolution that led to our species being here today is pure hubris and will lead to us hoisting ourselves by our own petard. Were the Butlerian Jihad were to start today, I know which side I’d find myself on. Stop boiling the damn ocean to make soulless art, worthless and insecure code, and education materials of which are lacking in facts. You have a brain; use it, exercise it, and find what you’re actually capable of.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Drunk Driving is OK in Canada</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/09/28/drunk-driving-is-ok-in-canada/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drunk Driving is OK in Canada" />
      
      <published>2024-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-09-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/09/28/drunk-driving-is-ok-in-canada</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/09/28/drunk-driving-is-ok-in-canada/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0niZCH57ngx5QVrE0_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press release from the Saskatchewan Party on September 13, 2024&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often I find myself writing about transit and thinking that many lives would not have been lost were we to have more publicly funded transit options. However, despite all of that, we have governments that don’t ever equate the use of transit and the reduction of vehicular alcohol abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/saskatoon/candidates-prior-dui-convictions-1.7327522&quot;&gt;The Saskatchewan Party released details about its slate of candidates ahead of the election writ being dropped&lt;/a&gt;. What was interesting was a line stating that there are five candidates who have past drunk driving charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott Moe, both current leader of the Saskatchewan Party and Premier of Saskatchewan, is also included in this list of having an impaired driving charge in 1992.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what is not mentioned here is that he has had t&lt;a href=&quot;https://pressprogress.ca/saskatchewan-premier-scott-moe-failed-to-disclose-his-other-impaired-driving-arrest-an-alleged-hit-and-run/&quot;&gt;wo other incidents including a 1994 charge of a hit-and-run and a 1997 collision that took the life of a mother of two sons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1994 incident, Scott Moe never received a breathalyzer test but did admit that he had consumed alcohol earlier in the day. However, there is a contradiction in all of this because this is what the police charge stating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…control of a motor vehicle that was involved in an accident with a vehicle at the Shellbrook Co-op with intent to escape civil or criminal liability, fail to stop his vehicle and give his name and address…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Moe clarifying in an interview when he was confronted over it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I exchanged information with the owner of the other vehicle and I called in the accident to the police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, since he apparently only called in the accident to police, there would be no evidence of him being under the influence at the time. We will just have to take him at his word that in 1997 when he killed 39-year old Joanne Bolog and injured her 18-year old son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No alcohol was cited here, but he was charged with driving without “due care” and “failing to come to a complete stop”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially rich considering that in 2019, the Humboldt Broncos junior hockey team &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humboldt_Broncos_bus_crash&quot;&gt;had sixteen players killed when their bus was hit by a truck&lt;/a&gt; in a much similar fashion. The driver of the truck, who was just a permanent resident at the time, is now &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/saskatchewan/humboldt-bus-driver-applies-to-reinstate-permanent-residency-1.7264031&quot;&gt;facing deportation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott Moe &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalnews.ca/news/5137008/scott-moe-humboldt-broncos-crash/&quot;&gt;commented on the tragedy&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Nobody sets out one morning with any intent of being in a car accident of any type […] [to] some degree I feel for Mr. Sidhu and his family.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moe is just lucky that he has a certain degree of privilege that lets him get away with his past behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could comment on other reasons for why &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/saskatoon/cupe-sask-moe-threat-statement-1.7157484&quot;&gt;Scott Moe (and his Saskatchewan Party) are a danger to others&lt;/a&gt;, but it doesn’t really matter what happens before you enter public life because it won’t matter when you are in office as Premier of a province anyhow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0-svaop15n5rNPAs3_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then-Premier of British Columbia, Gordon Campbell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 2003, while leaving friend and Vancouver-area broadcaster Fred Latremouille’s Hawaiian home, Premier Gordon Campbell was arrested and pled no contest to driving under the influence of alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Hawaii, it was merely a misdemeanour and not a criminal offence such as the case is in Canada, so he was fined US$913 and sent on his merry way under the condition he be checked for alcoholism and participate in a substance abuse program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calls for his resignation were made from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/b-c-premier-should-quit-over-drunk-driving-charge-madd-1.372946&quot;&gt;groups such as MADD&lt;/a&gt;, but he managed to survive another seven years in office only resigning in March 2011 after being bogged down by a poorly implemented sales tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drunk driving is OK because these two idiots never faced the music for it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Press release from the Saskatchewan Party on September 13, 2024 Often I find myself writing about transit and thinking that many lives would not have been lost were we to have more publicly funded transit options. However, despite all of that, we have governments that don’t ever equate the use of transit and the reduction of vehicular alcohol abuse. Earlier this month, The Saskatchewan Party released details about its slate of candidates ahead of the election writ being dropped. What was interesting was a line stating that there are five candidates who have past drunk driving charges. Scott Moe, both current leader of the Saskatchewan Party and Premier of Saskatchewan, is also included in this list of having an impaired driving charge in 1992. However, what is not mentioned here is that he has had two other incidents including a 1994 charge of a hit-and-run and a 1997 collision that took the life of a mother of two sons. In the 1994 incident, Scott Moe never received a breathalyzer test but did admit that he had consumed alcohol earlier in the day. However, there is a contradiction in all of this because this is what the police charge stating: …control of a motor vehicle that was involved in an accident with a vehicle at the Shellbrook Co-op with intent to escape civil or criminal liability, fail to stop his vehicle and give his name and address… With Moe clarifying in an interview when he was confronted over it: I exchanged information with the owner of the other vehicle and I called in the accident to the police. Of course, since he apparently only called in the accident to police, there would be no evidence of him being under the influence at the time. We will just have to take him at his word that in 1997 when he killed 39-year old Joanne Bolog and injured her 18-year old son. No alcohol was cited here, but he was charged with driving without “due care” and “failing to come to a complete stop”. Especially rich considering that in 2019, the Humboldt Broncos junior hockey team had sixteen players killed when their bus was hit by a truck in a much similar fashion. The driver of the truck, who was just a permanent resident at the time, is now facing deportation. Scott Moe commented on the tragedy: “Nobody sets out one morning with any intent of being in a car accident of any type […] [to] some degree I feel for Mr. Sidhu and his family.” Moe is just lucky that he has a certain degree of privilege that lets him get away with his past behaviour. I could comment on other reasons for why Scott Moe (and his Saskatchewan Party) are a danger to others, but it doesn’t really matter what happens before you enter public life because it won’t matter when you are in office as Premier of a province anyhow. Then-Premier of British Columbia, Gordon Campbell In January 2003, while leaving friend and Vancouver-area broadcaster Fred Latremouille’s Hawaiian home, Premier Gordon Campbell was arrested and pled no contest to driving under the influence of alcohol. In Hawaii, it was merely a misdemeanour and not a criminal offence such as the case is in Canada, so he was fined US$913 and sent on his merry way under the condition he be checked for alcoholism and participate in a substance abuse program. Calls for his resignation were made from groups such as MADD, but he managed to survive another seven years in office only resigning in March 2011 after being bogged down by a poorly implemented sales tax. Drunk driving is OK because these two idiots never faced the music for it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">British Rail and its attempt to sell Vancouver on a Railbus</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/09/13/british-rail-and-its-attempt-to-sell-vancouver-on-a-railbus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="British Rail and its attempt to sell Vancouver on a Railbus" />
      
      <published>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/09/13/british-rail-and-its-attempt-to-sell-vancouver-on-a-railbus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/09/13/british-rail-and-its-attempt-to-sell-vancouver-on-a-railbus/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0o557v1tTvd63pDNJ_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promotional image showing a Class 142 railbus somewhere in the Fraser Valley (British Rail)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme of Expo 86 was transportation and many, many countries took advantage of the show to demonstrate their developments in this field. Of course, the star of the show was Canada’s SkyTrain, but Japan showed its maglev train, America its cars, and the United Kingdom showed its conventional rail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/06Dah5PbvbOECUHR1_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said railbus being transported to Vancouver (Colin Arnot/RRPicturesArchives.NET)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British Rail, the then government corporation behind operation and development of rail transportation in the United Kingdom decided to send one of its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Rail_Class_142&quot;&gt;Class 142 train sets&lt;/a&gt; (aka “Pacer”) diesel trains (dubbed as “railbus”) to tour Metro Vancouver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They regularly ran service from a temporary station in Abbotsford to New Westminster during the summer months of 1986 along the railway once referred to as the Fraser Valley Line during the BC Electric Railway days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0GnkAjhGZcWGkhgiJ_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Railbus parked at the railyards in Strathcona (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did make an appearance near the Expo grounds at Pacific Central and was given a largely lukewarm reception by locals and government officials. The common critique of the train was the one shared by those back in the UK: it was an uncomfortable ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0mWXCaPSn8sHBJ0VX_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Railbus parked in New Westminster (J.W. Booth)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons behind the uncomfortable ride are known: unlike most trains, this was based on a bus made by British Leyland. A rail chassis was fixed to the bus body and then some slight modifications were made to the cab to make it “rail-ready”. Unlike a typical train, the wheels were fixed in place which made them noisy. To add to this, there were only two axels per car unlike the typical four you’d see on other trains including all of the ones used by SkyTrain today, which resulted in a rougher ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0UhOckj36dtTUra3X_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Railbus parked somewhere in the Fraser Valley (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the summer, the train set was sent back to the UK where it operated on various different services until all Pacers were retired at the end of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Promotional image showing a Class 142 railbus somewhere in the Fraser Valley (British Rail) The theme of Expo 86 was transportation and many, many countries took advantage of the show to demonstrate their developments in this field. Of course, the star of the show was Canada’s SkyTrain, but Japan showed its maglev train, America its cars, and the United Kingdom showed its conventional rail. Said railbus being transported to Vancouver (Colin Arnot/RRPicturesArchives.NET) British Rail, the then government corporation behind operation and development of rail transportation in the United Kingdom decided to send one of its Class 142 train sets (aka “Pacer”) diesel trains (dubbed as “railbus”) to tour Metro Vancouver. They regularly ran service from a temporary station in Abbotsford to New Westminster during the summer months of 1986 along the railway once referred to as the Fraser Valley Line during the BC Electric Railway days. Railbus parked at the railyards in Strathcona (City of Vancouver Archives) It did make an appearance near the Expo grounds at Pacific Central and was given a largely lukewarm reception by locals and government officials. The common critique of the train was the one shared by those back in the UK: it was an uncomfortable ride. Railbus parked in New Westminster (J.W. Booth) The reasons behind the uncomfortable ride are known: unlike most trains, this was based on a bus made by British Leyland. A rail chassis was fixed to the bus body and then some slight modifications were made to the cab to make it “rail-ready”. Unlike a typical train, the wheels were fixed in place which made them noisy. To add to this, there were only two axels per car unlike the typical four you’d see on other trains including all of the ones used by SkyTrain today, which resulted in a rougher ride. Railbus parked somewhere in the Fraser Valley (City of Vancouver Archives) After the summer, the train set was sent back to the UK where it operated on various different services until all Pacers were retired at the end of 2020.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The History of New Westminster Station</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/05/23/the-history-of-new-westminster-station/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The History of New Westminster Station" />
      
      <published>2024-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2024-05-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/05/23/the-history-of-new-westminster-station</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2024/05/23/the-history-of-new-westminster-station/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0ZfUm4OqObsWW8Wot_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BC Electric train at New Westminster Station during the Duke of Connaught visit (City of New Westminster)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0rmFGR3VLsRJuzHOE_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Westminster Station today&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who use New Westminster Station on the regular, it’s a place you either pass through, you get off to see a movie, or you catch a bus from to go up the steep hills of the city is named for. However, it has a long history of being a terminus going back to the early 20th Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original station building was located adjacent to the present-day station and is now a thrift store and office. It was opened in 1891 and sat directly next to the Canadian Pacific Railway’s station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0JSUn5MKtXyaYtCL5_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interurban as seen from the entrance of New Westminster Station (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a terminus for the Burnaby Lake and Central Park BC Electric Railway (BCER) interurban lines plus provided through service for the Vancouver to Chilliwack service as well. Add on top the street cars that littered New Westminster and a connection to Richmond (Lulu Island) and also to Vancouver via the Marpole line, you find yourself with a major hub for railway services in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0KUCSpRwM-pAo5GRA_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Westminster Station’s current location as seen in the early 1980s (City of New Westminster)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dissolution of passenger service provided by the BCER, New Westminster being a transportation hub in what was then Greater Vancouver came to an end. It became an area dominated by the car especially after the City of New Westminster opted to build a giant parkade on its waterfront in order to “revitalise” the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0rbh9XK4wG0DpORDk_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Westminster Station as seen in 1986 (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1985, New Westminster returned to being a transportation focal point with the opening of SkyTrain service and once again it became a terminus station. To facilitate it being a terminus station, half of the tracks were covered over with a temporary platform. This was because there was a planned extension to another station in the downtown area and then off to Surrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0exe-qvxG6-jAac7-_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Westminster Station as seen in the 1990s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This station became important to New Westminster’s efforts to revitalise its downtown core and in the 2000s, it became a focal point for densification. The former grounds of a car dealership, a parking lot, and a retail complex were all to be used as part of turning the station into a hub for residences and shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0nKYWEtWLAJ7XE0nO_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Westminster Station is now part of a shopping centre&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, New Westminster station is not only a hub for connections elsewhere in the city and beyond, but you can go there to get your groceries, eat a meal, and watch a movie. It even acts as an intermodal as a brief walk can take you to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newwestcity.ca/qtoqferry&quot;&gt;a ferry&lt;/a&gt; which connects downtown New Westminster with Queensborough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &lt;a href=&quot;https://dailyhive.com/vancouver/north-fraser-rapid-transit-line-vancouver-translink&quot;&gt;in the future it will be a connection to Vancouver via the old Marpole line&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">BC Electric train at New Westminster Station during the Duke of Connaught visit (City of New Westminster) New Westminster Station today For those who use New Westminster Station on the regular, it’s a place you either pass through, you get off to see a movie, or you catch a bus from to go up the steep hills of the city is named for. However, it has a long history of being a terminus going back to the early 20th Century. The original station building was located adjacent to the present-day station and is now a thrift store and office. It was opened in 1891 and sat directly next to the Canadian Pacific Railway’s station. Interurban as seen from the entrance of New Westminster Station (City of Vancouver Archives) It was a terminus for the Burnaby Lake and Central Park BC Electric Railway (BCER) interurban lines plus provided through service for the Vancouver to Chilliwack service as well. Add on top the street cars that littered New Westminster and a connection to Richmond (Lulu Island) and also to Vancouver via the Marpole line, you find yourself with a major hub for railway services in the region. New Westminster Station’s current location as seen in the early 1980s (City of New Westminster) With the dissolution of passenger service provided by the BCER, New Westminster being a transportation hub in what was then Greater Vancouver came to an end. It became an area dominated by the car especially after the City of New Westminster opted to build a giant parkade on its waterfront in order to “revitalise” the area. New Westminster Station as seen in 1986 (City of Vancouver Archives) In 1985, New Westminster returned to being a transportation focal point with the opening of SkyTrain service and once again it became a terminus station. To facilitate it being a terminus station, half of the tracks were covered over with a temporary platform. This was because there was a planned extension to another station in the downtown area and then off to Surrey. New Westminster Station as seen in the 1990s This station became important to New Westminster’s efforts to revitalise its downtown core and in the 2000s, it became a focal point for densification. The former grounds of a car dealership, a parking lot, and a retail complex were all to be used as part of turning the station into a hub for residences and shopping. New Westminster Station is now part of a shopping centre Today, New Westminster station is not only a hub for connections elsewhere in the city and beyond, but you can go there to get your groceries, eat a meal, and watch a movie. It even acts as an intermodal as a brief walk can take you to a ferry which connects downtown New Westminster with Queensborough. Perhaps in the future it will be a connection to Vancouver via the old Marpole line? This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">All about Mission City station</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/08/21/all-about-mission-city-station/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All about Mission City station" />
      
      <published>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/08/21/all-about-mission-city-station</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/08/21/all-about-mission-city-station/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0oJAwhQO1zQh0PCt5_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think about TransLink, you think about how it goes as far north as Lions Bay, as far south as White Rock, and as far west as Bowen Island. However, it does offer services outside of what is traditionally thought of as Metro Vancouver and that is where the curious case of Mission City station comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0xklzDo5285T-QGLO_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opened in 1995, Mission City station is the easternmost TransLink-operated service and yet Mission itself is not under the jurisdiction of TransLink; instead it’s BC Transit. Its West Coast Express service only operates on weekdays minus holidays with five trains in the morning towards Vancouver with them all returning in the evening to then be serviced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0kvoXsoJc1O1eW-hm_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of these times, bus service to Coquitlam Central is provided but only on the days the West Coast Express operates. With one bus late in the morning, one mid-afternoon, and two in the evening, its existence is solely to be supportive to commuters and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the pandemic, the station handled under 550 passengers per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BC Transit service is available all day and has connections all over Mission and to parts of Abbotsford. It’s one of two train stations operated by TransLink which another agency provide service to; the other being Lougheed Town Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0FNIXll_fI3w8ryoM_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also the only point where the West Coast Express and Via Rail, Canada’s national passenger railway service, meet even though the stop for Via is located at another station located 300 metres away down track at Mission Harbour Road. However, this sort of wasn’t always the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0ZjWMt28htRcp9NfE_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the dissolution of passenger rail service by the Canadian Pacific Railway, Mission Junction was the city’s railway station. Named for the junction which Mission City sits just east of, the station was located on the west side and became a heritage building in the early-1980s. Service to the station ceased in 1990 and for five years the street known as Railway Street which it sat on lacked a station until the West Coast Express came into being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, a fire in 1999 burnt down the original CPR station and it is suspected that arson played responsibility. Prior to the fire, plans were made to turn it into some sort of community hall but a lack of funds led to it being disused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">When you think about TransLink, you think about how it goes as far north as Lions Bay, as far south as White Rock, and as far west as Bowen Island. However, it does offer services outside of what is traditionally thought of as Metro Vancouver and that is where the curious case of Mission City station comes in. Opened in 1995, Mission City station is the easternmost TransLink-operated service and yet Mission itself is not under the jurisdiction of TransLink; instead it’s BC Transit. Its West Coast Express service only operates on weekdays minus holidays with five trains in the morning towards Vancouver with them all returning in the evening to then be serviced. Outside of these times, bus service to Coquitlam Central is provided but only on the days the West Coast Express operates. With one bus late in the morning, one mid-afternoon, and two in the evening, its existence is solely to be supportive to commuters and nothing more. Prior to the pandemic, the station handled under 550 passengers per day. BC Transit service is available all day and has connections all over Mission and to parts of Abbotsford. It’s one of two train stations operated by TransLink which another agency provide service to; the other being Lougheed Town Centre. It’s also the only point where the West Coast Express and Via Rail, Canada’s national passenger railway service, meet even though the stop for Via is located at another station located 300 metres away down track at Mission Harbour Road. However, this sort of wasn’t always the case. Prior to the dissolution of passenger rail service by the Canadian Pacific Railway, Mission Junction was the city’s railway station. Named for the junction which Mission City sits just east of, the station was located on the west side and became a heritage building in the early-1980s. Service to the station ceased in 1990 and for five years the street known as Railway Street which it sat on lacked a station until the West Coast Express came into being. Sadly, a fire in 1999 burnt down the original CPR station and it is suspected that arson played responsibility. Prior to the fire, plans were made to turn it into some sort of community hall but a lack of funds led to it being disused. This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">What decided the Skytrain line colours?</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/07/28/what-decided-the-skytrain-line-colours/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What decided the Skytrain line colours?" />
      
      <published>2023-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/07/28/what-decided-the-skytrain-line-colours</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/07/28/what-decided-the-skytrain-line-colours/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0mwdVIW4QbNPz8Ynu_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post has been sitting with me for a long while: why do the three SkyTrain lines have the colours they have today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the Millennium Line, it’s coloured as yellow; the Expo Line is coloured as blue, and the Canada Line is light blue. The latter is weird I must admit, but it might help to explain the history of colouring on SkyTrain maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0S2D8Lc_LtKrTbfQb_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the original SkyTrain map. No mention of an Expo Line because it was all that existed when it opened for Expo 86, the World’s Fair hosted here in Vancouver. It was a simple line which ran from Waterfront to New Westminster. The line was coloured in red and that is curious because it was pretty standard for BC Transit and its predecessor BC Hydro née BC Electric Railway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0eSlu6tTnzer1CfUq_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this 1930s map, all of the street cars and interurbans were given a red line. It might seem confusing to look at, but being that the transit network went to where people lived and people lived near the street cars and interurbans, it was fairly simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0p0MYRSmDOIBk3QxH_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually when maps needed to provide information about fares being charged by zone, the red colour went away in favour of black and stuck for nearly two decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/07MVwmnDu-fiHaNQ8_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TransLink inherited the colour scheme from BC Transit and continued to mark bus routes as red. With the opening of the Millennium Line and subsequent naming of the original SkyTrain line becoming “Expo” in honour of its origins, colours were needed to differentiate their service separate from buses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why yellow and blue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0GhXU5iUkuFriqoNK_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue should be an easy colour to talk about. SkyTrain was opened in time for Expo 86.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0pswJpNOEnwpiYJJw_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the Expo logo itself, we see a blue and this was the primary colour for the fair itself. With blue being the colour of Expo and being one of the primary colours used for the original SkyTrain livery, it stands to reason the best choice was a dark blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Expo was easy, but then why is the Millennium Line given a yellow colour? The naming is straightforward, it was opened in time to mark the new millennium, but the colour is strange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be safe to assume one thing: look at the political parties in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/06kus87FCawnLp1St_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political party in provincial power at the time of SkyTrain’s inauguration was Social Credit (Socred). Their primary colours were blue and red and they were not too dissimilar from BC Transit’s livery and in turn SkyTrain’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0yKehYHjHInKB0R-o_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, the NDP colours were not orange as we know them now but instead blue, yellow, and red. The Millennium Line was an NDP project and it is safe to assume that the colour chosen was purely to have one that wasn’t that of the Socreds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the best explanation I have because we see it play out when we talk about the Canada Line, because then things get weird. The Canada Line has a light blue colour, right? Let’s talk about some logos here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0R1-Qck_MaXmVdjIn_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at the SkyTrain logo adopted by TransLink when the Millennium Line opened, we see two colours atop of the “SkyTrain” text itself: blue and yellow. This logo was made to indicate the two lines of the then current SkyTrain system. So let’s see the logo used for the Canada Line when it was under construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0qBAJwm0ItamekRJ-_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the SkyTrain logo, we see two familiar lines, but then we see a red line added with a maple leaf at the tail just above “Canada Line”. It is safe to assume that during planning and construction that the Canada Line itself was going to have a red colour. So why the change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/06Ajhcr1qmrc4tUEf_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prevailing thought was that red was initially chosen as it was a colour of the BC Liberals. However, red is also the primary colour of the federal Liberal party. As provincial politics in British Columbia are weird and the BC Liberals (now BC United) were not at all associated with the federal party other than by name (unlike the NDP), it &lt;a href=&quot;https://dailyhive.com/vancouver/skytrain-canada-line-branding-name&quot;&gt;has been suggested&lt;/a&gt; that pressure from the Conservative Party likely led to the colour not being adopted in order to secure funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0zaRsmVkCOvP6K-8i_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether or not this is the case is hard to say, but there has been another instance where a colour was chosen for a rapid transit project for purely political reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0F9ptmIpDweNTBqd7_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extension of the Millennium Line into Coquitlam in 2016 was originally slated to be its own individual light rail line. It’s a recurring theme to have light rail become SkyTrain in Metro Vancouver and the “Evergreen Line” was eventually replaced by the “Evergreen extension” for a brief period of time after it was established it would integrated into the existing network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0GL7JkrjvJRbBZSk-_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a few years, the Millennium Line had a separate indicator for its Tri-cities extension only because &lt;a href=&quot;https://vancouversun.com/news/metro/translink-considers-changing-name-of-evergreen-line&quot;&gt;the mayors of the time wanted it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Though he said he understands TransLink’s intent to keep the name consistent with the Millennium Line, he said that name for that line has never made sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The mayor suggested SkyTrain lines could be renamed for their actual destinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We still think it’s a problem that needs a better solution than what TransLink initially proposed,” he said, adding the city suggested Evergreen-Millennium, but that was turned down because it was too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“They’ve got some work to do clearly, they’ve [TransLink] gone down the path to having it renamed the Millennium Line without telling anybody.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Port Moody Mayor Mike Clay is equally unimpressed with the idea of a name change for the new line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You just don’t give up on your brand,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“People buy into a brand, people identify with it locally. So the Evergreen Line is our line in the Tri-Cities, it’s always been that way. We’ve always identified with it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven years later and nobody refers to it as “Evergreen”-anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0natzDf-3-9ryzdQV_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current SkyTrain map shows a standard yellow colour and makes no mention of the special name given. The branding does remain in the stations themselves, but if the network is ever extended into Port Coquitlam, it is difficult to say whether or not it would keep it all. It should be kept in mind that these same demands never came from Vancouver for its extension to Arbutus or from Surrey or Langley for the extension out into the valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one more colour to talk about before I close this off: pink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0DfpoA5HJA_5egjDv_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0aMbjg_AO9QJSBJGn_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When SkyTrain has maintenance or must run a special service when dealing with station upgrades, the colour pink has been reserved to indicate that it is temporary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it: the colours chosen to represent the lines on the map are either purely political or something is disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">This post has been sitting with me for a long while: why do the three SkyTrain lines have the colours they have today? If we look at the Millennium Line, it’s coloured as yellow; the Expo Line is coloured as blue, and the Canada Line is light blue. The latter is weird I must admit, but it might help to explain the history of colouring on SkyTrain maps. This is the original SkyTrain map. No mention of an Expo Line because it was all that existed when it opened for Expo 86, the World’s Fair hosted here in Vancouver. It was a simple line which ran from Waterfront to New Westminster. The line was coloured in red and that is curious because it was pretty standard for BC Transit and its predecessor BC Hydro née BC Electric Railway. In this 1930s map, all of the street cars and interurbans were given a red line. It might seem confusing to look at, but being that the transit network went to where people lived and people lived near the street cars and interurbans, it was fairly simple. Eventually when maps needed to provide information about fares being charged by zone, the red colour went away in favour of black and stuck for nearly two decades. TransLink inherited the colour scheme from BC Transit and continued to mark bus routes as red. With the opening of the Millennium Line and subsequent naming of the original SkyTrain line becoming “Expo” in honour of its origins, colours were needed to differentiate their service separate from buses. So why yellow and blue? Blue should be an easy colour to talk about. SkyTrain was opened in time for Expo 86. If we look at the Expo logo itself, we see a blue and this was the primary colour for the fair itself. With blue being the colour of Expo and being one of the primary colours used for the original SkyTrain livery, it stands to reason the best choice was a dark blue. So Expo was easy, but then why is the Millennium Line given a yellow colour? The naming is straightforward, it was opened in time to mark the new millennium, but the colour is strange. It would be safe to assume one thing: look at the political parties in power. The political party in provincial power at the time of SkyTrain’s inauguration was Social Credit (Socred). Their primary colours were blue and red and they were not too dissimilar from BC Transit’s livery and in turn SkyTrain’s. In the 1990s, the NDP colours were not orange as we know them now but instead blue, yellow, and red. The Millennium Line was an NDP project and it is safe to assume that the colour chosen was purely to have one that wasn’t that of the Socreds. This is the best explanation I have because we see it play out when we talk about the Canada Line, because then things get weird. The Canada Line has a light blue colour, right? Let’s talk about some logos here. If we look at the SkyTrain logo adopted by TransLink when the Millennium Line opened, we see two colours atop of the “SkyTrain” text itself: blue and yellow. This logo was made to indicate the two lines of the then current SkyTrain system. So let’s see the logo used for the Canada Line when it was under construction. Like the SkyTrain logo, we see two familiar lines, but then we see a red line added with a maple leaf at the tail just above “Canada Line”. It is safe to assume that during planning and construction that the Canada Line itself was going to have a red colour. So why the change? The prevailing thought was that red was initially chosen as it was a colour of the BC Liberals. However, red is also the primary colour of the federal Liberal party. As provincial politics in British Columbia are weird and the BC Liberals (now BC United) were not at all associated with the federal party other than by name (unlike the NDP), it has been suggested that pressure from the Conservative Party likely led to the colour not being adopted in order to secure funding. Whether or not this is the case is hard to say, but there has been another instance where a colour was chosen for a rapid transit project for purely political reasons. The extension of the Millennium Line into Coquitlam in 2016 was originally slated to be its own individual light rail line. It’s a recurring theme to have light rail become SkyTrain in Metro Vancouver and the “Evergreen Line” was eventually replaced by the “Evergreen extension” for a brief period of time after it was established it would integrated into the existing network. For a few years, the Millennium Line had a separate indicator for its Tri-cities extension only because the mayors of the time wanted it. Though he said he understands TransLink’s intent to keep the name consistent with the Millennium Line, he said that name for that line has never made sense. The mayor suggested SkyTrain lines could be renamed for their actual destinations. “We still think it’s a problem that needs a better solution than what TransLink initially proposed,” he said, adding the city suggested Evergreen-Millennium, but that was turned down because it was too long. “They’ve got some work to do clearly, they’ve [TransLink] gone down the path to having it renamed the Millennium Line without telling anybody.” Port Moody Mayor Mike Clay is equally unimpressed with the idea of a name change for the new line. “You just don’t give up on your brand,” he said. “People buy into a brand, people identify with it locally. So the Evergreen Line is our line in the Tri-Cities, it’s always been that way. We’ve always identified with it.” Seven years later and nobody refers to it as “Evergreen”-anything. The current SkyTrain map shows a standard yellow colour and makes no mention of the special name given. The branding does remain in the stations themselves, but if the network is ever extended into Port Coquitlam, it is difficult to say whether or not it would keep it all. It should be kept in mind that these same demands never came from Vancouver for its extension to Arbutus or from Surrey or Langley for the extension out into the valley. There is one more colour to talk about before I close this off: pink. When SkyTrain has maintenance or must run a special service when dealing with station upgrades, the colour pink has been reserved to indicate that it is temporary. So there you have it: the colours chosen to represent the lines on the map are either purely political or something is disrupted. This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The Successor to the Mark I SkyTrain</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/07/05/the-successor-to-the-mark-i-skytrain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Successor to the Mark I SkyTrain" />
      
      <published>2023-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/07/05/the-successor-to-the-mark-i-skytrain</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/07/05/the-successor-to-the-mark-i-skytrain/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0Ffo9pt2M3YT-oAq8_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After SkyTrain was extended to Scott Road in 1991 and plans were put in place to extend it to the Expo Line’s current terminus, King George, there was a lot of talk by BC Transit and the then ruling Social Credit (Socred) government of the time on where to take Metro Vancouver’s transit network next. With more service means more trains and BC Transit made it a point to investigate its options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test Vehicle 06 or “TV06” was brought over from Urban Transportation Development Corporation’s facility in Kingston, Ontario. UTDC were the creators of the original SkyTrain technology and vehicles, so it was a natural fit for them to be involved with the creation of a successor vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UTDC’s approach was simple: take an existing Mark I vehicle and extend it. What was interesting about their approach was that the vehicle they chose was used on the SkyTrain demonstration line in 1983.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0FZSEkEdhYHn0n5eG_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vehicles used for the demonstration were the property of UTDC and had been used for testing and sales purposes after they returned home. UTDC decided that one of the vehicles would be better served as a test platform for a longer version of the vehicle with an additional door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0wLNvOV-2A-Kgokv7_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BC Transit continued to investigate options for the future of SkyTrain including hiring a film production crew to build a mockup train. This train was made of wood and while I cannot confirm, I have read that it was put on display at the 1991 Pacific National Exhibition (PNE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0K04WYrsm_e2NVq0y_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0LkYmAZJVQ481nyWV_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These trains may look familiar despite never having made any revenue service appearance, as this version of the Mark II was eventually used for Kuala Lumpur’s metro system. They were sold as cheaper than existing SkyTrain vehicles, could hold twice as many people per car, and were of course still compatible with the existing system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, plans were about to briefly change with an upcoming election. The sitting Socred government lost handily to the New Democratic Party (NDP) in the 1991 fall election. This new government had long been skeptical of SkyTrain and wanted to implement light rail (LRT) as opposed to advanced light rail (ALRT).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0O8Wp21GqsxdEl1BP_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story around the Millennium Line potentially becoming LRT too deserves its own article, but suffice to say, after a few years, this idea was abandoned sometime after Premier Mike Harcourt resigned and Glen Clark took his place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He favoured going back to SkyTrain and in 1998, his government had BC Transit partner with Bombardier, UTDC’s successor to not only use ALRT technology for the new line, but to also build the trains right next to SkyTrain’s maintenance facility in Burnaby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0Iy0fbquRhap-SHDZ_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “dummy” train was made and tested on the Expo Line during the planning stages for the new vehicles. It had no powertrain and thus had to be pushed around, but it was used to provide data to BC Transit and Bombardier for the development of a new train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0DV8sc9eDz3U9HYkW_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, the Mark II test vehicle started to venture on the now Expo Line. For the most part, tests were flawless and minus a few tweaks to the line itself such as changes to switches or placement of track indicators, they eventually entered revenue service in 2001 just in time for 2002’s opening of the Millennium Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mark IIs and Mark Is were a common sight on both lines. However, the Mark IIs were more popular as they had features such as air conditioning and were considerably quieter in operation. Exiting a Mark II train during the morning or afternoon rush was also much easier thanks to having three doors and more space when standing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Mark I is still a common sight on the Expo Line, they are approaching nearly four decades in use for the original train sets and despite a refurbishment programme starting in 2013, they are due to be retired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/09QNBfaKLYF4u7ywG_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later this year, Mark V trains will be delivered from Alstom, who has since acquired Bombardier. A total of 41 new train sets have been ordered to replace the aging Mark I fleet and to allow for the extension of the Millennium Line to Arbutus to meet expected capacity needs. By 2026, these new trains will completely replace the Mark Is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally hope someone acquires one of the Mark I pairs and opens a coffee shop inside of one called the “Expresso Line”. If you like that idea and want to run with it, it’s free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portions of this article were sourced from&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://buzzer.translink.ca/2019/04/translink-20-the-secret-mark-ii-skytrain-cars/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;this Buzzer piece&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;written back in April 2019. This was also originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">After SkyTrain was extended to Scott Road in 1991 and plans were put in place to extend it to the Expo Line’s current terminus, King George, there was a lot of talk by BC Transit and the then ruling Social Credit (Socred) government of the time on where to take Metro Vancouver’s transit network next. With more service means more trains and BC Transit made it a point to investigate its options. Test Vehicle 06 or “TV06” was brought over from Urban Transportation Development Corporation’s facility in Kingston, Ontario. UTDC were the creators of the original SkyTrain technology and vehicles, so it was a natural fit for them to be involved with the creation of a successor vehicle. UTDC’s approach was simple: take an existing Mark I vehicle and extend it. What was interesting about their approach was that the vehicle they chose was used on the SkyTrain demonstration line in 1983. The vehicles used for the demonstration were the property of UTDC and had been used for testing and sales purposes after they returned home. UTDC decided that one of the vehicles would be better served as a test platform for a longer version of the vehicle with an additional door. BC Transit continued to investigate options for the future of SkyTrain including hiring a film production crew to build a mockup train. This train was made of wood and while I cannot confirm, I have read that it was put on display at the 1991 Pacific National Exhibition (PNE). These trains may look familiar despite never having made any revenue service appearance, as this version of the Mark II was eventually used for Kuala Lumpur’s metro system. They were sold as cheaper than existing SkyTrain vehicles, could hold twice as many people per car, and were of course still compatible with the existing system. However, plans were about to briefly change with an upcoming election. The sitting Socred government lost handily to the New Democratic Party (NDP) in the 1991 fall election. This new government had long been skeptical of SkyTrain and wanted to implement light rail (LRT) as opposed to advanced light rail (ALRT). The story around the Millennium Line potentially becoming LRT too deserves its own article, but suffice to say, after a few years, this idea was abandoned sometime after Premier Mike Harcourt resigned and Glen Clark took his place. He favoured going back to SkyTrain and in 1998, his government had BC Transit partner with Bombardier, UTDC’s successor to not only use ALRT technology for the new line, but to also build the trains right next to SkyTrain’s maintenance facility in Burnaby. A “dummy” train was made and tested on the Expo Line during the planning stages for the new vehicles. It had no powertrain and thus had to be pushed around, but it was used to provide data to BC Transit and Bombardier for the development of a new train. In 2000, the Mark II test vehicle started to venture on the now Expo Line. For the most part, tests were flawless and minus a few tweaks to the line itself such as changes to switches or placement of track indicators, they eventually entered revenue service in 2001 just in time for 2002’s opening of the Millennium Line. The Mark IIs and Mark Is were a common sight on both lines. However, the Mark IIs were more popular as they had features such as air conditioning and were considerably quieter in operation. Exiting a Mark II train during the morning or afternoon rush was also much easier thanks to having three doors and more space when standing. While the Mark I is still a common sight on the Expo Line, they are approaching nearly four decades in use for the original train sets and despite a refurbishment programme starting in 2013, they are due to be retired. Later this year, Mark V trains will be delivered from Alstom, who has since acquired Bombardier. A total of 41 new train sets have been ordered to replace the aging Mark I fleet and to allow for the extension of the Millennium Line to Arbutus to meet expected capacity needs. By 2026, these new trains will completely replace the Mark Is. I personally hope someone acquires one of the Mark I pairs and opens a coffee shop inside of one called the “Expresso Line”. If you like that idea and want to run with it, it’s free. Portions of this article were sourced from this Buzzer piece written back in April 2019. This was also originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Downtown Vancouver’s railway</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/06/15/downtown-vancouver-s-railway/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Downtown Vancouver’s railway" />
      
      <published>2023-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-06-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/06/15/downtown-vancouver-s-railway</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/06/15/downtown-vancouver-s-railway/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0MsdyiKFA2H2Rn3hC_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shopping centre with a disused railway going through&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0FWhHHKCX8tJlHZdL_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map showing its old path&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself wandering in and around Chinatown and Gastown, you might notice an alleyway that there is an alleyway that goes on an angle from the port to International Village shopping centre, with its entrance continuing this path towards about where Stadium-Chinatown station stands today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what is left of a railway that connected the Canadian National Railway’s (CNR) yard in what is today Yaletown plus other railway services to the Canadian Pacific (CPR) yard near the Port of Vancouver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0lA12bteJ9S9ANsO3_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to 1932, the CPR’s only option to reach Burrard Inlet was a pathway that crossed through a cut in Vancouver’s busy city centre. The railway intersected with the busy streets of Pender and Hastings and passed the BC Electric Railway’s downtown terminus at Carrall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0rz1kOPqjw__5Swrr_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unsurprising produced a great deal of congestion for the city and railway. The railway needed to get mail, freight, and passengers around quickly and the city wanted fewer accidents. At a cost of CA$1.6 million (or about CA$33 million in 2023), a tunnel was built under Dunsmuir street to then s-curve to an exit at about Burrard Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0B3wzy99bKrGIt_0X_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPR trains could now quickly loop around to their station at what is now Waterfront and no longer have to find themselves at odds with other railway traffic or people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tunnel would keep its importance until passenger and freight services to the area ceased in 1982. It would then eventually become the underground portion of the Expo Line we have on the SkyTrain system today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/08CUYjBz_Ny7JwhyY_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the former surface railway, it had become disused and over time development in the area turned it into a parking lot, a beautified alley, and the main hall of a shopping centre. It seems that both the tunnel and the cut it replaced have survived in their own ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Shopping centre with a disused railway going through Map showing its old path If you find yourself wandering in and around Chinatown and Gastown, you might notice an alleyway that there is an alleyway that goes on an angle from the port to International Village shopping centre, with its entrance continuing this path towards about where Stadium-Chinatown station stands today. This is what is left of a railway that connected the Canadian National Railway’s (CNR) yard in what is today Yaletown plus other railway services to the Canadian Pacific (CPR) yard near the Port of Vancouver. Prior to 1932, the CPR’s only option to reach Burrard Inlet was a pathway that crossed through a cut in Vancouver’s busy city centre. The railway intersected with the busy streets of Pender and Hastings and passed the BC Electric Railway’s downtown terminus at Carrall. This unsurprising produced a great deal of congestion for the city and railway. The railway needed to get mail, freight, and passengers around quickly and the city wanted fewer accidents. At a cost of CA$1.6 million (or about CA$33 million in 2023), a tunnel was built under Dunsmuir street to then s-curve to an exit at about Burrard Street. CPR trains could now quickly loop around to their station at what is now Waterfront and no longer have to find themselves at odds with other railway traffic or people. This tunnel would keep its importance until passenger and freight services to the area ceased in 1982. It would then eventually become the underground portion of the Expo Line we have on the SkyTrain system today. As for the former surface railway, it had become disused and over time development in the area turned it into a parking lot, a beautified alley, and the main hall of a shopping centre. It seems that both the tunnel and the cut it replaced have survived in their own ways. This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The other Royal visit to train 014 and SkyTrain’s influence abroad</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/05/17/the-other-royal-visit-to-train-014-and-skytrain-s-influence-abroad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The other Royal visit to train 014 and SkyTrain’s influence abroad" />
      
      <published>2023-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/05/17/the-other-royal-visit-to-train-014-and-skytrain-s-influence-abroad</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/05/17/the-other-royal-visit-to-train-014-and-skytrain-s-influence-abroad/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0CBizWYtYWu4-CK6W_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Princess Diana walking along the platform of Patterson Station in 1986 (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0l-DHvDFBc33VHmrK_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prince Charles (now King Charles III) and Princess Diana greeting two people (Vancouver Province)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1986, during Expo ’86, King Charles III (then Prince) and his then wife, Princess Diana paid a visit to Patterson Station in Burnaby to see the new rapid transit system. They boarded car 014, dubbed the “Spirit of Canada”, and made history as the first visiting monarch to use the transit system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this visit overshadows another royal visit and one that had substantial ramifications for the country the monarch heralded from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0QTm3wU80YxCMeYsN_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaque as seen on train 014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 8th, 1989, Thailand’s Princess Chulabhorn paid a visit to Vancouver and rode on the very same car the Prince and Princess of Wales rode three years prior. Ten years later, Thailand’s capital city, Bangkok would open its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BTS_Skytrain&quot;&gt;BTS Skytrain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0F5UP8DmgM932SFeD_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTS Skytrain vehicles passing each other (author unknown)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike the Vancouver SkyTrain (note the upper case ‘T’ in our name), Bangkok’s system did not use trains from Bombardier and instead its initial set were from Siemens. The reason for the name was that the original system proposal was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lavalin_Skytrain&quot;&gt;Lavalin Skytrain&lt;/a&gt;, as SNC Lavalin itself was responsible for the construction of Vancouver’s system. This project was cancelled in 1992 officially due to financial reasons, but it was suggested politics played a role in its demise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason, despite SNC Lavalin’s lack of involvement in the succeeding project, the name “Skytrain” stuck and in 1999, the Bangkok Mass Transit System officially opened and named as “BTS Skytrain”. Perhaps the Princess just liked the name? Who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Princess Diana walking along the platform of Patterson Station in 1986 (City of Vancouver Archives) Prince Charles (now King Charles III) and Princess Diana greeting two people (Vancouver Province) In 1986, during Expo ’86, King Charles III (then Prince) and his then wife, Princess Diana paid a visit to Patterson Station in Burnaby to see the new rapid transit system. They boarded car 014, dubbed the “Spirit of Canada”, and made history as the first visiting monarch to use the transit system. However, this visit overshadows another royal visit and one that had substantial ramifications for the country the monarch heralded from. Plaque as seen on train 014 On May 8th, 1989, Thailand’s Princess Chulabhorn paid a visit to Vancouver and rode on the very same car the Prince and Princess of Wales rode three years prior. Ten years later, Thailand’s capital city, Bangkok would open its BTS Skytrain. BTS Skytrain vehicles passing each other (author unknown) However, unlike the Vancouver SkyTrain (note the upper case ‘T’ in our name), Bangkok’s system did not use trains from Bombardier and instead its initial set were from Siemens. The reason for the name was that the original system proposal was the Lavalin Skytrain, as SNC Lavalin itself was responsible for the construction of Vancouver’s system. This project was cancelled in 1992 officially due to financial reasons, but it was suggested politics played a role in its demise. For whatever reason, despite SNC Lavalin’s lack of involvement in the succeeding project, the name “Skytrain” stuck and in 1999, the Bangkok Mass Transit System officially opened and named as “BTS Skytrain”. Perhaps the Princess just liked the name? Who knows. This was originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Ghosts: Connaught Hill</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/04/06/ghosts-connaught-hill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ghosts: Connaught Hill" />
      
      <published>2023-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/04/06/ghosts--connaught-hill</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/04/06/ghosts-connaught-hill/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0EQSQDDm2kBZUHNGs_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximate location of the former station, Connaught Hill (Google Street View)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When riding down the Expo Line from Edmonds to 22nd Street, one may notice that it is a rather lengthy ride. At nearly 2 KM, it’s nowhere near the longest distance between stations, but when it was the interurban Central Park Line, there was a station in-between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BC Electric Railway (BCER) had a station around what is now 9th Avenue in Burnaby or simply situated south of a SkyTrain maintenance facility. Connaught Hill, named after after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provinces_of_Ireland&quot;&gt;western province of Ireland named Connaught&lt;/a&gt;, was a small station serving the now-residential area straddling the Burnaby and New Westminster border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0aDPvuKJ2ViH0_2Wj_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Station location in New Westminster (Google)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back then, it was a large gravel pit. The hole created conveniently ended up becoming the SkyTrain maintenance facility we have today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0SBkId7uE8qauIaEM_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connaught Hill as it appeared in the 1950s (TransLink / BC Transit)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there sits no station but you can visit its old location when travelling along the BC Parkway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0VJJ4ymcv-f55a5Cj_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stopped to take a photo as I cycled on by. You can see the remnants of the old tracks left behind.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Approximate location of the former station, Connaught Hill (Google Street View) When riding down the Expo Line from Edmonds to 22nd Street, one may notice that it is a rather lengthy ride. At nearly 2 KM, it’s nowhere near the longest distance between stations, but when it was the interurban Central Park Line, there was a station in-between the two. The BC Electric Railway (BCER) had a station around what is now 9th Avenue in Burnaby or simply situated south of a SkyTrain maintenance facility. Connaught Hill, named after after the western province of Ireland named Connaught, was a small station serving the now-residential area straddling the Burnaby and New Westminster border. Station location in New Westminster (Google) Back then, it was a large gravel pit. The hole created conveniently ended up becoming the SkyTrain maintenance facility we have today. Connaught Hill as it appeared in the 1950s (TransLink / BC Transit) Today, there sits no station but you can visit its old location when travelling along the BC Parkway. Stopped to take a photo as I cycled on by. You can see the remnants of the old tracks left behind.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Harvie Rd. and Surrey’s Lost Railway</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/02/05/harvie-rd-and-surrey-s-lost-railway/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harvie Rd. and Surrey’s Lost Railway" />
      
      <published>2023-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/02/05/harvie-rd--and-surrey-s-lost-railway</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/02/05/harvie-rd-and-surrey-s-lost-railway/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0k0whuKnn8tiOHj-r_1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map showing the Port Kells area of Surrey (Google)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few years, you’ll be able to ride SkyTrain all the way into Langley, passing by one of Cloverdale’s quiet landmarks: the Honeybee Centre. However, if you go just the building, you’ll notice a road that runs on an angle, which is odd considering most of Surrey’s roads tend to run in cardinal directions save for Fraser Highway and a few others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harvie Rd. is a shortcut from Port Kells to the rest of Surrey, but its origins as a road do not come from being a shortcut but instead a railway. There are a few roads that do not conform to the grid system and they too share this history as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0mCx-epomuxyTCg6j_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximate path that the railway took&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1891, the New Westminster-Southern Railway opened a passenger railway crossing across the US border into Cloverdale and then to New Westminster via Port Kells. This route followed what is now Highway 15 with a deviation around a hill in Hazlemere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, it was the only rail service connecting the United States and Canada west of the Rockies. Its construction was of major concern to the federal government due to possible threat to sovereignty by the Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/09Kn3oJF2bWpXBsfc_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southern portion of the railway about 3 KM north of the United States border&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1907, the Great Northern Railway, the parent company to the NWSR, opted to reroute all rail service to its line which straddled the Semiahmoo peninsula and subsequently ended its inland rail connection going through Blaine. The NWSR struggled to remain competitive in the face of the BC Electric Railway providing similar service, which intersected in Cloverdale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1929, the railway was declared abandoned and as time has gone on much of the right of way has been usurped by the highway it once ran alongside. However, remnants of it are still visible if you know where to look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0NodtNz7s3b7Id41I_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harvey Rd. as seen from near the Port Kells Library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for road itself, it got its name from NWSR’s first engineer, Robert Harvie. It has since received heritage right of way status from the City of Surrey, which protects it as a roadway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you’re interested in additional information,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://oppositethecity.wordpress.com/2014/02/12/new-westminster-southern-railway-survey/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;this blog article from 2014&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;is also worth a read! I used the custom Google Maps link they created to generate the above maps.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is also a post archived from cohost.org/VancouverTransit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Map showing the Port Kells area of Surrey (Google) In a few years, you’ll be able to ride SkyTrain all the way into Langley, passing by one of Cloverdale’s quiet landmarks: the Honeybee Centre. However, if you go just the building, you’ll notice a road that runs on an angle, which is odd considering most of Surrey’s roads tend to run in cardinal directions save for Fraser Highway and a few others. Harvie Rd. is a shortcut from Port Kells to the rest of Surrey, but its origins as a road do not come from being a shortcut but instead a railway. There are a few roads that do not conform to the grid system and they too share this history as well. Approximate path that the railway took In 1891, the New Westminster-Southern Railway opened a passenger railway crossing across the US border into Cloverdale and then to New Westminster via Port Kells. This route followed what is now Highway 15 with a deviation around a hill in Hazlemere. For some time, it was the only rail service connecting the United States and Canada west of the Rockies. Its construction was of major concern to the federal government due to possible threat to sovereignty by the Americans. Southern portion of the railway about 3 KM north of the United States border In 1907, the Great Northern Railway, the parent company to the NWSR, opted to reroute all rail service to its line which straddled the Semiahmoo peninsula and subsequently ended its inland rail connection going through Blaine. The NWSR struggled to remain competitive in the face of the BC Electric Railway providing similar service, which intersected in Cloverdale. By 1929, the railway was declared abandoned and as time has gone on much of the right of way has been usurped by the highway it once ran alongside. However, remnants of it are still visible if you know where to look. Harvey Rd. as seen from near the Port Kells Library As for road itself, it got its name from NWSR’s first engineer, Robert Harvie. It has since received heritage right of way status from the City of Surrey, which protects it as a roadway. If you’re interested in additional information, this blog article from 2014 is also worth a read! I used the custom Google Maps link they created to generate the above maps. This is also a post archived from cohost.org/VancouverTransit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Commercial-Broadway could have been Clark-Broadway?</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/01/18/commercial-broadway-could-have-been-clark-broadway/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Commercial-Broadway could have been Clark-Broadway?" />
      
      <published>2023-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2023-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/01/18/commercial-broadway-could-have-been-clark-broadway</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2023/01/18/commercial-broadway-could-have-been-clark-broadway/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0E40es-COMsWtWIGr_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commercial Drive and Broadway circa 1940s with a street car 5 going downtown and an interurban going to New Westminster (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intersection of Commercial Drive and Broadway is today a major interchange station between SkyTrain’s Millennium and Expo lines, and the rapid bus 99 B-Line. Historically, this area has been of major importance the two BC Electric Railway’s interurban lines which served east Vancouver (the Central Park and Burnaby Lake lines) merged with the street car serving Commercial Drive to then feed into downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this produced a major choke point as having three different rail services interlining on a single street created serious congestion challenges for the BCER. A solution proposed in the 1920s was a proposal to extend the Central Park line from Victoria and Hull all the way to Main Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0BPgADZbNFsiOXQaq_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map showing railways around East Vancouver (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0Wd1A16bKZlY4Th6e_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking along Commercial as it bends to become Victoria&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would have extended the line northwest along the curve where Victoria turns into Commercial, then crossing Clark and Broadway, with a tunnel under St. Catherine’s Street, then following along E. 2nd Avenue until finally turning to cross False Creek, then finally terminating at the Great Northern Station located at Carrall and Keefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0jqmmAxvszw9_pM2Q_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very failed attempt at overlaying the old map and the current state, looking at Commercial and Broadway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/04yk_VxBdhGiE_zus_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same process but looking at the rail yards in and around Pacific Central and Terminal Ave&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overlaying the map from the 1930s on something modern takes a lot of guesswork as you can tell, but this gives you a pretty good idea of what the Expo Line could have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0nPU4gs9QMcPzlvE6_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lakeview station which was then a community garden but has since become housing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the onset of the Second World War and decade-later closure of the Central Park line, these plans were never meant to be. The modern Expo Line now turns away from what was then Cedar Cottage (now a community garden) and crosses over Broadway and Commercial to follow the Grandview cut towards downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, with the extension of the Millennium Line to Arbutus, a tunnel is now going to grace the neighbourhood of Mount Pleasant after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was an article originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit but moved here due to the site’s shutdown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Commercial Drive and Broadway circa 1940s with a street car 5 going downtown and an interurban going to New Westminster (City of Vancouver Archives) The intersection of Commercial Drive and Broadway is today a major interchange station between SkyTrain’s Millennium and Expo lines, and the rapid bus 99 B-Line. Historically, this area has been of major importance the two BC Electric Railway’s interurban lines which served east Vancouver (the Central Park and Burnaby Lake lines) merged with the street car serving Commercial Drive to then feed into downtown. However, this produced a major choke point as having three different rail services interlining on a single street created serious congestion challenges for the BCER. A solution proposed in the 1920s was a proposal to extend the Central Park line from Victoria and Hull all the way to Main Street. Map showing railways around East Vancouver (City of Vancouver Archives) Walking along Commercial as it bends to become Victoria This would have extended the line northwest along the curve where Victoria turns into Commercial, then crossing Clark and Broadway, with a tunnel under St. Catherine’s Street, then following along E. 2nd Avenue until finally turning to cross False Creek, then finally terminating at the Great Northern Station located at Carrall and Keefer. A very failed attempt at overlaying the old map and the current state, looking at Commercial and Broadway Same process but looking at the rail yards in and around Pacific Central and Terminal Ave Overlaying the map from the 1930s on something modern takes a lot of guesswork as you can tell, but this gives you a pretty good idea of what the Expo Line could have been. Lakeview station which was then a community garden but has since become housing With the onset of the Second World War and decade-later closure of the Central Park line, these plans were never meant to be. The modern Expo Line now turns away from what was then Cedar Cottage (now a community garden) and crosses over Broadway and Commercial to follow the Grandview cut towards downtown. That said, with the extension of the Millennium Line to Arbutus, a tunnel is now going to grace the neighbourhood of Mount Pleasant after all. This was an article originally posted to cohost.org/VancouverTransit but moved here due to the site’s shutdown.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Gilmore is the Oldest Original Millennium Line Station</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/12/19/gilmore-is-the-oldest-original-millennium-line-station/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gilmore is the Oldest Original Millennium Line Station" />
      
      <published>2022-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/12/19/gilmore-is-the-oldest-original-millennium-line-station</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/12/19/gilmore-is-the-oldest-original-millennium-line-station/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0QNNQWaR-TsuomG-j_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gilmore at platform-level&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to pull up information about the Millennium Line, you’d soon come across its opening date of January 7th, 2002. With that known, you’d then say that every station opened then as being the oldest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assumption is fairly safe as the line itself is a relatively new railway. Unlike the Expo Line, much of the initial alignment did not make use of a another railway’s existing or former right of way. This means that stations such as Sperling-Burnaby Lake or Lougheed Town Centre have no real historical reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is not entirely true for all of the stations which opened in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0QyUyB98d-dfJ_MVo_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view towards a right of way crossing at Gilmore and Henning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BC Electric Railway used to run a similar line to compliment the Central Park line named the Burnaby Lake line. It ran from New Westminster at the same spot the Central Park line did and merged with the street car line on Commercial Drive just its sibling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I should write about the Burnaby Lake line, but the point here is that the Millennium Line does intersect with the remnants of this line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0MBkHAJNxxQSe3tFL_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gilmore station as viewed from the same spot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s Gilmore Station is located at the intersection of the street bearing its name and Dawson. It’s probably one of the weirder stations in my opinion not because of anything other than its ceilings resembling curved plywood. I guess one can just go across the street to the Home Depot to pick up replacement panels should any of them fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the station’s previous incarnation was fairly unassuming and significantly more rural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0t8qOlS7mSp1YSnRz_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map showing GIlmore on the Burnaby Lake line (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original Gilmore Station from the Burnaby Lake line days was too at Gilmore and Dawson. It was to serve the swampy, agricultural area known as Still Creek. I could write extensively about the history of Still Creek, but really that was just it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the shutdown of the BCER in favour of trolley and diesel buses, it closed in 1956.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/01vzPO3p6Hb7D3rcO_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interurban travelling along the Burnaby Lake line (City of Burnaby Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference between the BCER station and the one we have today is where the current station stands. However, the original station site does continue serving a public good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/03xE-EbI-irla1Tfj_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View of the Gilmore Pump Station approximately where the original Gilmore station stood&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the site of the original BCER station is Gilmore Pump Station, which while does not serve rail traffic anymore, it does serve a function to make sure that if you were to come downstairs from the Millennium Line, you don’t encounter a giant puddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Gilmore at platform-level If you were to pull up information about the Millennium Line, you’d soon come across its opening date of January 7th, 2002. With that known, you’d then say that every station opened then as being the oldest. This assumption is fairly safe as the line itself is a relatively new railway. Unlike the Expo Line, much of the initial alignment did not make use of a another railway’s existing or former right of way. This means that stations such as Sperling-Burnaby Lake or Lougheed Town Centre have no real historical reference. However, this is not entirely true for all of the stations which opened in 2002. A view towards a right of way crossing at Gilmore and Henning The BC Electric Railway used to run a similar line to compliment the Central Park line named the Burnaby Lake line. It ran from New Westminster at the same spot the Central Park line did and merged with the street car line on Commercial Drive just its sibling. At some point, I should write about the Burnaby Lake line, but the point here is that the Millennium Line does intersect with the remnants of this line. Gilmore station as viewed from the same spot Today’s Gilmore Station is located at the intersection of the street bearing its name and Dawson. It’s probably one of the weirder stations in my opinion not because of anything other than its ceilings resembling curved plywood. I guess one can just go across the street to the Home Depot to pick up replacement panels should any of them fail. However, the station’s previous incarnation was fairly unassuming and significantly more rural. Map showing GIlmore on the Burnaby Lake line (City of Vancouver Archives) The original Gilmore Station from the Burnaby Lake line days was too at Gilmore and Dawson. It was to serve the swampy, agricultural area known as Still Creek. I could write extensively about the history of Still Creek, but really that was just it. As part of the shutdown of the BCER in favour of trolley and diesel buses, it closed in 1956. Interurban travelling along the Burnaby Lake line (City of Burnaby Archives) The main difference between the BCER station and the one we have today is where the current station stands. However, the original station site does continue serving a public good. View of the Gilmore Pump Station approximately where the original Gilmore station stood On the site of the original BCER station is Gilmore Pump Station, which while does not serve rail traffic anymore, it does serve a function to make sure that if you were to come downstairs from the Millennium Line, you don’t encounter a giant puddle. This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">When Stadium-Chinatown station also had monorail</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/11/10/when-stadium-chinatown-station-also-had-monorail/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Stadium-Chinatown station also had monorail" />
      
      <published>2022-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/11/10/when-stadium-chinatown-station-also-had-monorail</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/11/10/when-stadium-chinatown-station-also-had-monorail/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1zYXlaC4NP-rImwpQiVw3EA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plaza of Nations at Expo 86 (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expo 86 was Vancouver’s “coming out” party and its theme was transportation. This of course coincided with the opening of what is now the Expo Line from Waterfront to its then terminus at New Westminster. However, there were a few rapid transit systems built for the exposition including one very useful monorail system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/09xZnfaE659e4LuDG_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map showing the transfer point between then “Stadium” station to the Expo 86 monorail (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the event, a monorail platform was situated to the west of what was then Stadium station and it provided speedy service across the sprawling World’s Fair. The entire length of the service spanned over five kilometres and it was vital in not only connecting the parts of the False Creek portion of the fair, but also back to SkyTrain itself which was a link to the Canada Pavilion at what is now Canada Place, next to Waterfront station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0dZI2LWXKVjdtmJag_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monorail cruising through the Expo 86 grounds (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monorail itself had several other stops including two near what is now Yaletown-Roundhouse station on the Canada Line, inside of the Plaza of Nations near BC Place Stadium, one at the Cambie Street bridge, and one more just a block from Main Street-Science World (which would then have been just “Main Street” as Science World was simply “Expo Centre” during the fair).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1ee23Zt3FL6RZHW0fBowjOw_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expo 86 and the Monorail (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing about the monorail was that it was envisioned as a possible rapid transit system for Metro Vancouver as early as the 1950s (at some point I should write about this). However, when finally built, it simply hugged False Creek and after the fair was over, was dismantled and sent off to England where it became a staple of an amusement park starting in summer 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/02L8u8xcWbHQUrfJM_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposed tram or street car system (City of Vancouver)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The route it took however is still an option under consideration for a street car service (see green-coloured line above), but Vancouver City Council has been speaking about this idea for decades and it probably could be decades more before we ever see that happen &lt;a href=&quot;https://dailyhive.com/vancouver/downtown-vancouver-false-creek-streetcar-route-map&quot;&gt;even though as early as last year it had another report released on it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Plaza of Nations at Expo 86 (City of Vancouver Archives) Expo 86 was Vancouver’s “coming out” party and its theme was transportation. This of course coincided with the opening of what is now the Expo Line from Waterfront to its then terminus at New Westminster. However, there were a few rapid transit systems built for the exposition including one very useful monorail system. Map showing the transfer point between then “Stadium” station to the Expo 86 monorail (City of Vancouver Archives) During the event, a monorail platform was situated to the west of what was then Stadium station and it provided speedy service across the sprawling World’s Fair. The entire length of the service spanned over five kilometres and it was vital in not only connecting the parts of the False Creek portion of the fair, but also back to SkyTrain itself which was a link to the Canada Pavilion at what is now Canada Place, next to Waterfront station. Monorail cruising through the Expo 86 grounds (City of Vancouver Archives) The monorail itself had several other stops including two near what is now Yaletown-Roundhouse station on the Canada Line, inside of the Plaza of Nations near BC Place Stadium, one at the Cambie Street bridge, and one more just a block from Main Street-Science World (which would then have been just “Main Street” as Science World was simply “Expo Centre” during the fair). Expo 86 and the Monorail (City of Vancouver Archives) One interesting thing about the monorail was that it was envisioned as a possible rapid transit system for Metro Vancouver as early as the 1950s (at some point I should write about this). However, when finally built, it simply hugged False Creek and after the fair was over, was dismantled and sent off to England where it became a staple of an amusement park starting in summer 1987. Proposed tram or street car system (City of Vancouver) The route it took however is still an option under consideration for a street car service (see green-coloured line above), but Vancouver City Council has been speaking about this idea for decades and it probably could be decades more before we ever see that happen even though as early as last year it had another report released on it. This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">When Vancouver could have been like Edmonton and Calgary</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/10/25/when-vancouver-could-have-been-like-edmonton-and-calgary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Vancouver could have been like Edmonton and Calgary" />
      
      <published>2022-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/10/25/when-vancouver-could-have-been-like-edmonton-and-calgary</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/10/25/when-vancouver-could-have-been-like-edmonton-and-calgary/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0dnWjkMeMImTGo4SL_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light rail vehicle parked at a rail yard in New Westminster (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Vancouver dismantled its interurban railway network in the 1950s, it wasn’t long until local officials and the provincial government began to discuss options to recreate it in the form of a rapid transit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1970s, constant traffic problems and the oil crisis spurred the provincial government to start serious proposals for what would become the region’s rail system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0k1CgaptZ6nv3PZkD_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proposed rapid transit routes from the 1970s (University of British Columbia Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above map isn’t too dissimilar to what we have today (Hastings and North Shore do not have rail as of today), but the government’s idea was to quickly revive the old BC Electric Railway by strong-arming it into existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how do you force a railway to exist? By of course buying a Siemens vehicle from what was then West Germany to demonstrate the proposal along the Central Park BCER line (which is now the Expo Line).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1976, a succeeding government who didn’t like the purchase but had to receive it anyway opted to keep the train in storage. It languished in a rail yard in New Westminster until 1987 when it sold it to a group in Edmonton for a loonie. At some point in the last decade, it was returned to its native Germany where it now resides in a museum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0gSnxHOMeJhvDucRk_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public meeting announcement for rapid transit (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the government also had purchased back two former-BCER interurban vehicles from owners in Washington state. These two vehicles are still in Metro Vancouver with one residing in Steveston and the other in Cloverdale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t the first time LRT was proposed nor the last. Almost every planned LRT implementation in Metro Vancouver has turned into some sort of light metro. There is this desire to replicate the Edmonton LRT or Calgary C-Train for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps when the City of Vancouver finally implements its street car network we’ll finally have such trains in use in the region once again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Light rail vehicle parked at a rail yard in New Westminster (City of Vancouver Archives) When Vancouver dismantled its interurban railway network in the 1950s, it wasn’t long until local officials and the provincial government began to discuss options to recreate it in the form of a rapid transit. In the 1970s, constant traffic problems and the oil crisis spurred the provincial government to start serious proposals for what would become the region’s rail system. Proposed rapid transit routes from the 1970s (University of British Columbia Archives) The above map isn’t too dissimilar to what we have today (Hastings and North Shore do not have rail as of today), but the government’s idea was to quickly revive the old BC Electric Railway by strong-arming it into existence. And how do you force a railway to exist? By of course buying a Siemens vehicle from what was then West Germany to demonstrate the proposal along the Central Park BCER line (which is now the Expo Line). However, in 1976, a succeeding government who didn’t like the purchase but had to receive it anyway opted to keep the train in storage. It languished in a rail yard in New Westminster until 1987 when it sold it to a group in Edmonton for a loonie. At some point in the last decade, it was returned to its native Germany where it now resides in a museum. Public meeting announcement for rapid transit (City of Vancouver Archives) Interestingly, the government also had purchased back two former-BCER interurban vehicles from owners in Washington state. These two vehicles are still in Metro Vancouver with one residing in Steveston and the other in Cloverdale. It wasn’t the first time LRT was proposed nor the last. Almost every planned LRT implementation in Metro Vancouver has turned into some sort of light metro. There is this desire to replicate the Edmonton LRT or Calgary C-Train for some reason. Perhaps when the City of Vancouver finally implements its street car network we’ll finally have such trains in use in the region once again? This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Collingwood and Central Park</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/10/12/collingwood-and-central-park/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collingwood and Central Park" />
      
      <published>2022-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/10/12/collingwood-and-central-park</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/10/12/collingwood-and-central-park/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0awxO7VhBypP2pokN_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remnants of an overpass at Boundary and Vanness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s modern Vancouver, the section between Joyce-Collingwood and Patterson stations on the Expo Line is often seen as a relatively sleepy area with access to a large park, a corporate office for a major employer, and a connection to one of the Rapidbuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you have a keen eye and opt to walk along the route, you might stumble across some interesting history that makes this stretch of the SkyTrain network rather peculiar due to it having one of the few BC Electric Railway overpasses still left standing directly underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0WeCX5zmvLnGLSvzZ_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remnants of an overpass near Kingsway and Sandell on Smith&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Situated between Kingsway and Sandell on Smith, you’ll find this interesting little structure that is very much out of place and is towered over by the railway overhead. Today, it acts as an underpass for access to the office building on the other side, but beyond that it doesn’t have much of a purpose today. It likely still stands as there is a gas line which intersects underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0QIlQdgdnM4etbujc_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overpass as it appeared in the 1980s at Boundary and Vanness (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, until sometime in the 1990s, there was another overpass just 100 metres to the west at the intersection of Boundary and Vanness, which remained even after the Expo Line had opened. It was to serve the industrial complex which eventually became the various apartment and condominium buildings we know Joyce-Collingwood for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This likely resulted in a lack of need for the railway overpass to continue existing. For the most part it is now gone and now Boundary Road is now six lanes as opposed to four and it is still an uncomfortable connection for cyclists who wish to continue on the BC Parkway, which follows most of the Expo Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last part is a bit of a thorn in my side as the overpass could have served a use for cyclists who wanted to avoid having to make an awkward connection to the path on the Burnaby side. Aside from that, the whole overpass itself has some interesting history and could have been a station if BC Transit had its way in the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0WmySFcGhawnZ1iLI_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Map showing the Central Park line (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two stations on the above map do exist on the modern Expo Line: Patterson and Collingwood East, which is now Joyce-Collingwood. However, one other station on here labelled as Park Ave could have existed as it was a station under consideration when planning for the Expo Line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/0jDeB46Du3WlZqbLj_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View of what is now Boundary and Vanness in the 1940s (City of Vancouver Archives)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Park Ave was really what we today call Boundary Road and its station was situated directly behind what is now one of TELUS’ corporate office. As you can see in the above photo, the overpass is very much the same design as the one I paid a visit to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BC Transit planners were seriously considering a station called Boundary in that same spot. BCTel (who was gobbled up by TELUS in the late 1990s) was the province’s largest employer at the time and the government was keen to provide the office workers with access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why it never got built is unknown to me, but I imagine since the distance between Patterson and Joyce-Collingwood isn’t terribly long that they opted to not bother. As it would have straddled a zone boundary, it’s possible it could have produced a possible conflict. However, considering the existence of two consecutive stations with this fate on the Millennium Line, I think that is a moot point nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that remains today of Boundary Station, formerly Park Ave Station is just a retaining wall for the old BCER overpass which was torn down sometime three decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Remnants of an overpass at Boundary and Vanness In today’s modern Vancouver, the section between Joyce-Collingwood and Patterson stations on the Expo Line is often seen as a relatively sleepy area with access to a large park, a corporate office for a major employer, and a connection to one of the Rapidbuses. However, if you have a keen eye and opt to walk along the route, you might stumble across some interesting history that makes this stretch of the SkyTrain network rather peculiar due to it having one of the few BC Electric Railway overpasses still left standing directly underneath. Remnants of an overpass near Kingsway and Sandell on Smith Situated between Kingsway and Sandell on Smith, you’ll find this interesting little structure that is very much out of place and is towered over by the railway overhead. Today, it acts as an underpass for access to the office building on the other side, but beyond that it doesn’t have much of a purpose today. It likely still stands as there is a gas line which intersects underneath. Overpass as it appeared in the 1980s at Boundary and Vanness (City of Vancouver Archives) However, until sometime in the 1990s, there was another overpass just 100 metres to the west at the intersection of Boundary and Vanness, which remained even after the Expo Line had opened. It was to serve the industrial complex which eventually became the various apartment and condominium buildings we know Joyce-Collingwood for. This likely resulted in a lack of need for the railway overpass to continue existing. For the most part it is now gone and now Boundary Road is now six lanes as opposed to four and it is still an uncomfortable connection for cyclists who wish to continue on the BC Parkway, which follows most of the Expo Line. That last part is a bit of a thorn in my side as the overpass could have served a use for cyclists who wanted to avoid having to make an awkward connection to the path on the Burnaby side. Aside from that, the whole overpass itself has some interesting history and could have been a station if BC Transit had its way in the 1980s. Map showing the Central Park line (City of Vancouver Archives) Two stations on the above map do exist on the modern Expo Line: Patterson and Collingwood East, which is now Joyce-Collingwood. However, one other station on here labelled as Park Ave could have existed as it was a station under consideration when planning for the Expo Line. View of what is now Boundary and Vanness in the 1940s (City of Vancouver Archives) Park Ave was really what we today call Boundary Road and its station was situated directly behind what is now one of TELUS’ corporate office. As you can see in the above photo, the overpass is very much the same design as the one I paid a visit to. BC Transit planners were seriously considering a station called Boundary in that same spot. BCTel (who was gobbled up by TELUS in the late 1990s) was the province’s largest employer at the time and the government was keen to provide the office workers with access. Why it never got built is unknown to me, but I imagine since the distance between Patterson and Joyce-Collingwood isn’t terribly long that they opted to not bother. As it would have straddled a zone boundary, it’s possible it could have produced a possible conflict. However, considering the existence of two consecutive stations with this fate on the Millennium Line, I think that is a moot point nowadays. All that remains today of Boundary Station, formerly Park Ave Station is just a retaining wall for the old BCER overpass which was torn down sometime three decades ago. This originally appeared on cohost.org/VancouverTransit but has been moved here due to the site’s shutdown.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Porting Doom to A/UX</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/06/07/porting-doom-to-a-ux/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Porting Doom to A/UX" />
      
      <published>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/06/07/porting-doom-to-a-ux</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/06/07/porting-doom-to-a-ux/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since Doom was made open source, porting the game to run on anything with a display has been a hobby for programmers. From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7gCZZkBATSc&quot;&gt;digital cameras&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/diekmann/wasm-fizzbuzz&quot;&gt;web browsers&lt;/a&gt;, the game has touched any computer capable of running the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last May, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FOSSfirefighter&quot;&gt;NCommander&lt;/a&gt; released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XzhCGSE7KKw&quot;&gt;YouTube video documenting the perils of porting Doom&lt;/a&gt; to run on an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_RS/6000&quot;&gt;IBM RS/6000-series computer&lt;/a&gt; from the early 2000s, which cost at least US$10,000 at the time of its launch and ran &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_AIX&quot;&gt;AIX&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix&quot;&gt;UNIX operating system&lt;/a&gt; by the same manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never considered porting Doom before, but I was curious if my favourite abandoned UNIX variant had a port. With some very brief cursory searches on Google and GitHub, I was led to believe that this was unlikely or if it had been done, it was never publicly announced a port or it has been lost to the sands of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is the case nobody has bothered, there is a good reason: it isn’t exactly necessary. Once I explain A/UX, it’ll make sense why I am likely the first person ever to port the game to this platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What is A/UX?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Mac OS X (now macOS), Apple did have another operating system built on the foundations of UNIX. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A/UX&quot;&gt;A/UX&lt;/a&gt; was Apple’s UNIX implementation and it is a true UNIX in that it ran &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNIX_System_V&quot;&gt;AT&amp;amp;T System V&lt;/a&gt; under the hood, just like IBM AIX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its purpose was to give Apple a foothold within the United States government’s computer contracts as it provided the ease of the Finder interface with the power of UNIX, which was the backbone of many projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of this sounds weird already I am sure you are thinking; it is. A/UX is UNIX but it runs the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/System_7&quot;&gt;Macintosh System software&lt;/a&gt; as its own thread. This meant that your copy of Microsoft Office or Adobe Photoshop could run simultaneously with something like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COBOL&quot;&gt;COBOL&lt;/a&gt; application initially written in the 1970s on the same computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple maintained the operating system from 1988 through to 1995, at which point it was abandoned as it was written solely for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motorola_68000&quot;&gt;Motorola 68000&lt;/a&gt; series computer models — the company had moved on to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerPC&quot;&gt;PowerPC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardware requirements for the operating system were &lt;a href=&quot;https://gunkies.org/wiki/A/UX#Physical_Hardware&quot;&gt;rather steep&lt;/a&gt;. Most entry-level machines could not run it (really the vast majority including all PowerBooks) and the base models of any qualifying computer were often not sufficient either. It wasn’t ever meant to be used by the general public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MkLinux&quot;&gt;MkLinux&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copland_%28operating_system%29&quot;&gt;Copland&lt;/a&gt; came along around its demise as well, but they too were abandoned when &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NeXT&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/a&gt; was bought by Apple and subsequent development on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhapsody_%28operating_system%29&quot;&gt;Rhapsody&lt;/a&gt; led to the release of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mac_OS_X_10.0&quot;&gt;Mac OS X&lt;/a&gt;, ending the use of the legacy operating system Apple was formerly chained to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, both Mac OS X and A/UX share one thing in common: the ability to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classic_Mac_OS#Classic&quot;&gt;execute classic Mac applications atop of a multithreaded operating system&lt;/a&gt;. Macintosh System didn’t have any &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooperative_multitasking&quot;&gt;true multitasking&lt;/a&gt; and was a rather inferior operating system in contrast, but these two operating systems got around that problem in a rather effective manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Preparing to port Doom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have had a &lt;a href=&quot;https://everymac.com/systems/apple/mac_quadra/specs/mac_quadra_800.html&quot;&gt;Quadra 800&lt;/a&gt; with 64 MB of RAM sitting in my closet for a long time. I’ve streamed it a few times and have it to thank for a speedrun that failed due to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.makeuseof.com/softlock-hardlock-in-video-games-explained/&quot;&gt;softlock&lt;/a&gt; (Mario’s Time Machine Deluxe, which I hold the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.speedrun.com/marios_time_machine/run/y91qrprm&quot;&gt;solo world record for on the Windows release&lt;/a&gt;), but it has never really been used to its full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/UX has been something I have always been curious about and I’ve maintained an SD card with an install of it for my Quadra for a few years — this is helped by my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codesrc.com/mediawiki/index.php/SCSI2SD&quot;&gt;SCSI2SD&lt;/a&gt;. Having seen Doom ported to AIX with all of its challenges made me wonder about doing it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself am not very confident in my programming abilities despite my online username, but I figured I was capable enough so I went forward. My primary language is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;, but I had written C on embedded systems and figured my knowledge was enough to take a crack at this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest and final release of A/UX was version 3.1.1 in 1995. Doom was released a few years prior and was itself developed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NeXTSTEP&quot;&gt;NeXTSTEP&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that the code should with some work port over quite easily as it was meant to use X11 from the ground up — this is the windowing system the majority of UNIX operating systems used then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;June 8, 2022 — Whoa. What a mistake I made with the last paragraph. NeXTSTEP used Display PostScript, which isn’t like X11 at all. I completely overlooked this fact considering OS X’s display mechanism. Anyway, I am leaving the above as is.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/UX has an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_Window_System&quot;&gt;X11&lt;/a&gt; environment, but I wanted to use its full experience: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finder_%28software%29&quot;&gt;Finder environment&lt;/a&gt; it came with — you can switch between them easily at the login prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1iGspneVfKl2XCo7IY7jhmw_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Login options from a computer running A/UX.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a choice between a console emulator, a 24-bit or 32-bit Finder, or X11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve this, this required the use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacX&quot;&gt;MacX&lt;/a&gt;, an X11 implementation also abandoned by Apple. This software permits the use of the system on any Mac seamlessly within the Finder — and it is not just limited to A/UX-running systems either, but that is a different topic all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1sy_6XC69SPgPE7OcBq5LkA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Same computer but loading MacX atop of A/UX.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“High-performance” by 1997 standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the base system ready, I also needed some other tools: namely the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gcc.gnu.org&quot;&gt;GNU GCC compiler&lt;/a&gt; and its various components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, someone who worked at NASA had for almost a decade after A/UX’s demise maintained ports of modern-ish software — a mirror is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://polysoft.fr/jagubox/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This meant that I had the ability to use version 2.7.2 of GCC plus a myriad of other required tools to both compile the software and also not make me pull my hair out. Additionally, you can find other useful software including OpenSSH via &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.preterhuman.net/Newbie_Guide_To_A/UX_%28Apple_UNIX%29#Getting_Newer_Software_Packages&quot;&gt;other mirrors&lt;/a&gt;, which made transferring files easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Doom itself, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/id-Software/DOOM&quot;&gt;source code has been freely available for decades&lt;/a&gt;. All you need to make it run post-compilation is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://doom.fandom.com/wiki/WAD&quot;&gt;WAD file&lt;/a&gt;, which contains all of the assets for the game to run. Most Doom releases over the decades have included this file in one form or another and I had both the &lt;a href=&quot;https://doomwiki.org/wiki/DOOM1.WAD&quot;&gt;shareware&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://doomwiki.org/wiki/DOOM.WAD&quot;&gt;retail&lt;/a&gt; releases handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the tools and the pieces, but now I had to do the hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You can’t just make this stuff up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often when you get source code, you can just browse to the directory and type ‘make’ at the command line to have it compile into something useful. This is almost the case here with Doom on A/UX, but its codebase expects you to be building for Linux instead and very quickly you are presented with problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound was designed for Linux for one and unfortunately &lt;a href=&quot;https://venam.nixers.net/blog/unix/2021/02/07/audio-stack.html&quot;&gt;isn’t simple or consistent&lt;/a&gt; across UNIX and UNIX-like operating systems — &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opensound.com&quot;&gt;OSS&lt;/a&gt; is not an option either. I didn’t feel like dealing with this mess, so I commented out all instances of sound and music in the source code. I could have just changed the code to just do nothing, but I was admittedly looking for the quick way out rather than build something flagged at compile time to contend with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being that A/UX is also ancient in the operating system sense, a lot of functions that would be included in anything made in the past thirty years are missing. Fortunately, these functions are limited to the use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/manual/html_node/Advantages-of-Alloca.html&quot;&gt;alloca&lt;/a&gt;, which can be replaced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/manual/html_node/Basic-Allocation.html&quot;&gt;malloc&lt;/a&gt; (with some extra code); and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/docs/en/i/7.1?topic=functions-strnicmp-compare-substrings-without-case-sensitivity&quot;&gt;strcmpi&lt;/a&gt;, which I just commented out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latter’s removal had a slight consequence: the WAD file, which contains the game content, now must have a lowercase filename as that function’s task is to do a string comparison without case sensitivity. It didn’t exist in GCC until just after the turn of the millennium so we either had to remove it or write something in its place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doom does a file scan in the same directory as where it is executed from for files matching the extension “wad” upon launch, so my workaround is an annoyance but reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One joke about the Motorola 68000 architecture is that it’s basically “backwards x86” — 68000 is abbreviated as “68k” and if you reverse it you get “k86” (get it?). At an instruction level, there is an unsurprising overlap between the two, but honestly where the joke lands at is that it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endianness&quot;&gt;big endian as opposed to little&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This presents a problem with these WAD files as their byte order is meant for a little endian system, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.osdev.org/Endianness&quot;&gt;while is the case for x86, it is not for the 68000&lt;/a&gt;. I had to add compiler flags to make use of the built-ins which manage this problem and fortunately that was the last hurdle to get the game to actually load and seemingly function on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1jmEO0sU423adpa69HLU8UQ_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of me editing C code on a Twitch stream.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reversing a suggestion to run these as signed as opposed to unsigned was the last hurdle after adding a compiler flag to force use of the functions if the flag is used. After this point, I had success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small thing: I had left networking untouched in the code, but I disabled at compile time as it was presenting problems. However, I think it would be neat to take &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FOSSfirefighter/status/1534207951686230016&quot;&gt;NCommander’s suggestion&lt;/a&gt; of trying to do something akin to a deathmatch between two different dinosaur systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;It works, but it’s slow and has other problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After two evenings worth of streaming on Twitch my making code changes and testing on actual hardware, one compile finally led to it executing. I actually didn’t expect the last fix to be the final task remaining to make it run as expected, but it did and for the first time we had Doom running natively on A/UX in an X11 window within Finder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the lack of sound and having to tell MacX to let me use the arrow keys as desired (apparently mouse emulation with them is a default), the game was running at maybe 2–3 frames per second. Lowering the graphic details improved things a bit, but adjusting the overall screen size in-game netted no change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1B4lfzySGpzoBlAXXdoP7DA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Doom being played in A/UX.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becky Heineman’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Olde-Skuul/doom3do/blob/master/README.md&quot;&gt;README&lt;/a&gt; file for the 3DO Doom port comes to mind now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keybindings also restricted me to anything but move around, change weapons, select menu options, and open doors — I was unable to shoot enemies, which is an objective in winning the game. However, I was able to get from the start of the first level in Episode 1 to the exit, meaning that I was able to play the game in a pacifist setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1p3TcII70yhqeegwijBgFJQ_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a Mac running A/UX with a level completed in Doom.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it to the end of the level with no kills, but I did at least one secret! Also, someone asked if this was real hardware, so I made my &lt;a href=&quot;https://videogameperfection.com/products/open-source-scan-converter/&quot;&gt;OSSC&lt;/a&gt; show the display details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the frame rate problem remained. The running theory I have is that since MacX is running the game in Finder which itself is a process in A/UX, the game has to traverse through the TCP network stack to output to Finder, meaning there is additional CPU overhead. The 33 MHz processor is handling the operating system, Finder, MacX, networking, and Doom all at the same time, so as a consequence, the visuals suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did to tackle the problem was to set the compiler flags to automatically optimise the code just so we can at least improve the existing situation. This is all handled by GCC itself with &lt;a href=&quot;https://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc/Optimize-Options.html&quot;&gt;a simple flag&lt;/a&gt; and the consequences of doing so should be (and “should be” is key) additional memory use and longer compilation time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t add much to the latter and the memory use was inconsequential, but the graphics rendering absolutely suffered with little improvement to the frame rate. Effectively I turned a slideshow that looked otherwise normal into a slideshow resembling a music video for a vaporwave single. So let’s not enable this option for now I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1rXCaHVgsvmwdcZjCYd-oLQ_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Doom showing visual artifacting as I move the game around.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least the HUD was normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to find a reason for why using this flag led to this problem, but it could be many things and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/article/18/8/what-how-makefile&quot;&gt;Makefile&lt;/a&gt; in the original source doesn’t have them enabled anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem I have right now is that X11 doesn’t wish to be a solo session on my A/UX install and I cannot figure out why. My only guess is that maybe it might hate my &lt;a href=&quot;https://apple.fandom.com/wiki/Radius#Accelerator_cards&quot;&gt;Radius graphics accelerator&lt;/a&gt;, but I haven’t had the time to diagnose this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I am confident that the performance problem resides with the sandwich Doom must crawl through to make it to my eyeballs and that running it in a pure X11 session is the best way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to figure this out for yourself however!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why am I (likely) the first to do this?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there are two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that A/UX is obscure. It never really had a market outside of the US government and organisations associated with it. Even with its largest customer, it had an extremely small user base and its abandonment accelerated its irrelevance. You’re more likely to find an RS/6000 running AIX today than a Quadra 900 running A/UX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obscurity is also hastened by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aux-penelope.com/hardware.htm&quot;&gt;hardware it runs on&lt;/a&gt; often never being intended for the at home market. The only mainstream Mac I can think of capable of running it was the SE/30. It’s “mainstream” in the sense that it appeared in Seinfeld as a prop in Jerry’s apartment for several seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, with it pre-installed on a Macintosh, it would set you back &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.ca/books?id=Cz8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA31&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;almost US$10,000 in the late 1980s&lt;/a&gt;, or about US$25,000 in 2022 money. This was never meant for the average end user!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason is the least likely but came to mind: Doom sort of can run on A/UX already. When I say “sort of”, I am referring to A/UX’s Finder implementation which gives a System 7.0.1 environment. The caveat here is that &lt;a href=&quot;https://doomwiki.org/wiki/Doom_%28Apple_Macintosh%29&quot;&gt;Doom requires System 7.1&lt;/a&gt;, but with a few hacks and tweaks, &lt;a href=&quot;http://christtrekker.users.sourceforge.net/doc/aux/faq.html#EmulSys71&quot;&gt;you can run a later version&lt;/a&gt; of the system software albeit with the loss of certain components which makes A/UX itself useful alongside Mac software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Quadra’s processor while sluggish should not be a problem in running this game I must add, but these older CPUs are single-threaded and can only do much at a time. Doom may seem like a really simple game by modern standards (and it is really &lt;a href=&quot;https://doom.fandom.com/wiki/Doom_rendering_engine&quot;&gt;a glorified 2D one&lt;/a&gt;), but it was cutting edge when it came out in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, because of its obscurity and hardware requirements plus emulation capable of running the OS still in its infancy (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pruten/shoebill&quot;&gt;Shoebill&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://virtuallyfun.com/wordpress/2021/09/02/qemus-macintosh-quadra-in-alpha-usability-runs-a-ux/&quot;&gt;QEMU&lt;/a&gt; are the only options as of this writing), it is likely that my hobbyist exposure plus my love of Doom finally led to an attempt to build the game to run on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The help I received when I streamed my porting attempts definitely made this possible as well, so it was not a solo effort I must admit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up until this point, my knowledge of any operating system development was limited to Linux, macOS, and Windows, but I guess I can now say I know a little bit about AT&amp;amp;T System V and its A/UX variant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Where can I get this?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source code is available on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/KateLibC/auxdoom-1.10&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and a compiled binary is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/KateLibC/auxdoom-1.10/releases&quot;&gt;available there too&lt;/a&gt;. I have no intention to update this further beyond maybe a few tweaks to make it more playable. If you wish to make changes on your own, feel free to fork it or just send me pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure to read the README before compiling as there are a few steps you might need to take in order to get it up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea if the emulators capable of running A/UX can even run this game and I have even less of a clue whether you can run this on anything earlier than version 3.1.1 of the operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have the two streams where I worked on it archived on YouTube (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ce8Mx5PDe1c&quot;&gt;June 5th&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gNB3D0OAjKw&quot;&gt;June 6th&lt;/a&gt; were their recordings), but do give me a follow on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/katelibc&quot;&gt;Twitch&lt;/a&gt; as well as I stream speedrunning, visual novel games, and occasionally stuff like this.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Ever since Doom was made open source, porting the game to run on anything with a display has been a hobby for programmers. From digital cameras to web browsers, the game has touched any computer capable of running the code. Last May, NCommander released a YouTube video documenting the perils of porting Doom to run on an IBM RS/6000-series computer from the early 2000s, which cost at least US$10,000 at the time of its launch and ran AIX, a UNIX operating system by the same manufacturer. I’ve never considered porting Doom before, but I was curious if my favourite abandoned UNIX variant had a port. With some very brief cursory searches on Google and GitHub, I was led to believe that this was unlikely or if it had been done, it was never publicly announced a port or it has been lost to the sands of time. If it is the case nobody has bothered, there is a good reason: it isn’t exactly necessary. Once I explain A/UX, it’ll make sense why I am likely the first person ever to port the game to this platform. What is A/UX? Prior to Mac OS X (now macOS), Apple did have another operating system built on the foundations of UNIX. A/UX was Apple’s UNIX implementation and it is a true UNIX in that it ran AT&amp;amp;T System V under the hood, just like IBM AIX. Its purpose was to give Apple a foothold within the United States government’s computer contracts as it provided the ease of the Finder interface with the power of UNIX, which was the backbone of many projects. And all of this sounds weird already I am sure you are thinking; it is. A/UX is UNIX but it runs the Macintosh System software as its own thread. This meant that your copy of Microsoft Office or Adobe Photoshop could run simultaneously with something like a COBOL application initially written in the 1970s on the same computer. Apple maintained the operating system from 1988 through to 1995, at which point it was abandoned as it was written solely for the Motorola 68000 series computer models — the company had moved on to PowerPC. Hardware requirements for the operating system were rather steep. Most entry-level machines could not run it (really the vast majority including all PowerBooks) and the base models of any qualifying computer were often not sufficient either. It wasn’t ever meant to be used by the general public. Other projects like MkLinux and Copland came along around its demise as well, but they too were abandoned when Next was bought by Apple and subsequent development on Rhapsody led to the release of Mac OS X, ending the use of the legacy operating system Apple was formerly chained to. Interestingly, both Mac OS X and A/UX share one thing in common: the ability to execute classic Mac applications atop of a multithreaded operating system. Macintosh System didn’t have any true multitasking and was a rather inferior operating system in contrast, but these two operating systems got around that problem in a rather effective manner. Preparing to port Doom I have had a Quadra 800 with 64 MB of RAM sitting in my closet for a long time. I’ve streamed it a few times and have it to thank for a speedrun that failed due to a softlock (Mario’s Time Machine Deluxe, which I hold the solo world record for on the Windows release), but it has never really been used to its full potential. A/UX has been something I have always been curious about and I’ve maintained an SD card with an install of it for my Quadra for a few years — this is helped by my SCSI2SD. Having seen Doom ported to AIX with all of its challenges made me wonder about doing it myself. I myself am not very confident in my programming abilities despite my online username, but I figured I was capable enough so I went forward. My primary language is Python, but I had written C on embedded systems and figured my knowledge was enough to take a crack at this. The latest and final release of A/UX was version 3.1.1 in 1995. Doom was released a few years prior and was itself developed on NeXTSTEP, meaning that the code should with some work port over quite easily as it was meant to use X11 from the ground up — this is the windowing system the majority of UNIX operating systems used then. June 8, 2022 — Whoa. What a mistake I made with the last paragraph. NeXTSTEP used Display PostScript, which isn’t like X11 at all. I completely overlooked this fact considering OS X’s display mechanism. Anyway, I am leaving the above as is. A/UX has an X11 environment, but I wanted to use its full experience: the Finder environment it came with — you can switch between them easily at the login prompt. You have a choice between a console emulator, a 24-bit or 32-bit Finder, or X11. In order to achieve this, this required the use of MacX, an X11 implementation also abandoned by Apple. This software permits the use of the system on any Mac seamlessly within the Finder — and it is not just limited to A/UX-running systems either, but that is a different topic all together. “High-performance” by 1997 standards. Having the base system ready, I also needed some other tools: namely the GNU GCC compiler and its various components. Fortunately, someone who worked at NASA had for almost a decade after A/UX’s demise maintained ports of modern-ish software — a mirror is available here. This meant that I had the ability to use version 2.7.2 of GCC plus a myriad of other required tools to both compile the software and also not make me pull my hair out. Additionally, you can find other useful software including OpenSSH via other mirrors, which made transferring files easy. As for Doom itself, the source code has been freely available for decades. All you need to make it run post-compilation is a WAD file, which contains all of the assets for the game to run. Most Doom releases over the decades have included this file in one form or another and I had both the shareware and retail releases handy. I had the tools and the pieces, but now I had to do the hard work. You can’t just make this stuff up Often when you get source code, you can just browse to the directory and type ‘make’ at the command line to have it compile into something useful. This is almost the case here with Doom on A/UX, but its codebase expects you to be building for Linux instead and very quickly you are presented with problems. Sound was designed for Linux for one and unfortunately isn’t simple or consistent across UNIX and UNIX-like operating systems — OSS is not an option either. I didn’t feel like dealing with this mess, so I commented out all instances of sound and music in the source code. I could have just changed the code to just do nothing, but I was admittedly looking for the quick way out rather than build something flagged at compile time to contend with this. Being that A/UX is also ancient in the operating system sense, a lot of functions that would be included in anything made in the past thirty years are missing. Fortunately, these functions are limited to the use of alloca, which can be replaced by malloc (with some extra code); and strcmpi, which I just commented out. The latter’s removal had a slight consequence: the WAD file, which contains the game content, now must have a lowercase filename as that function’s task is to do a string comparison without case sensitivity. It didn’t exist in GCC until just after the turn of the millennium so we either had to remove it or write something in its place. Doom does a file scan in the same directory as where it is executed from for files matching the extension “wad” upon launch, so my workaround is an annoyance but reasonable. One joke about the Motorola 68000 architecture is that it’s basically “backwards x86” — 68000 is abbreviated as “68k” and if you reverse it you get “k86” (get it?). At an instruction level, there is an unsurprising overlap between the two, but honestly where the joke lands at is that it’s big endian as opposed to little. This presents a problem with these WAD files as their byte order is meant for a little endian system, which while is the case for x86, it is not for the 68000. I had to add compiler flags to make use of the built-ins which manage this problem and fortunately that was the last hurdle to get the game to actually load and seemingly function on its own. Reversing a suggestion to run these as signed as opposed to unsigned was the last hurdle after adding a compiler flag to force use of the functions if the flag is used. After this point, I had success! One small thing: I had left networking untouched in the code, but I disabled at compile time as it was presenting problems. However, I think it would be neat to take NCommander’s suggestion of trying to do something akin to a deathmatch between two different dinosaur systems. It works, but it’s slow and has other problems After two evenings worth of streaming on Twitch my making code changes and testing on actual hardware, one compile finally led to it executing. I actually didn’t expect the last fix to be the final task remaining to make it run as expected, but it did and for the first time we had Doom running natively on A/UX in an X11 window within Finder. Aside from the lack of sound and having to tell MacX to let me use the arrow keys as desired (apparently mouse emulation with them is a default), the game was running at maybe 2–3 frames per second. Lowering the graphic details improved things a bit, but adjusting the overall screen size in-game netted no change. Becky Heineman’s README file for the 3DO Doom port comes to mind now. Keybindings also restricted me to anything but move around, change weapons, select menu options, and open doors — I was unable to shoot enemies, which is an objective in winning the game. However, I was able to get from the start of the first level in Episode 1 to the exit, meaning that I was able to play the game in a pacifist setting. I made it to the end of the level with no kills, but I did at least one secret! Also, someone asked if this was real hardware, so I made my OSSC show the display details. But the frame rate problem remained. The running theory I have is that since MacX is running the game in Finder which itself is a process in A/UX, the game has to traverse through the TCP network stack to output to Finder, meaning there is additional CPU overhead. The 33 MHz processor is handling the operating system, Finder, MacX, networking, and Doom all at the same time, so as a consequence, the visuals suffer. The first thing I did to tackle the problem was to set the compiler flags to automatically optimise the code just so we can at least improve the existing situation. This is all handled by GCC itself with a simple flag and the consequences of doing so should be (and “should be” is key) additional memory use and longer compilation time. It didn’t add much to the latter and the memory use was inconsequential, but the graphics rendering absolutely suffered with little improvement to the frame rate. Effectively I turned a slideshow that looked otherwise normal into a slideshow resembling a music video for a vaporwave single. So let’s not enable this option for now I guess. At least the HUD was normal. I tried to find a reason for why using this flag led to this problem, but it could be many things and the Makefile in the original source doesn’t have them enabled anyway. The problem I have right now is that X11 doesn’t wish to be a solo session on my A/UX install and I cannot figure out why. My only guess is that maybe it might hate my Radius graphics accelerator, but I haven’t had the time to diagnose this. However, I am confident that the performance problem resides with the sandwich Doom must crawl through to make it to my eyeballs and that running it in a pure X11 session is the best way to go. Feel free to figure this out for yourself however! Why am I (likely) the first to do this? I think there are two reasons. The first is that A/UX is obscure. It never really had a market outside of the US government and organisations associated with it. Even with its largest customer, it had an extremely small user base and its abandonment accelerated its irrelevance. You’re more likely to find an RS/6000 running AIX today than a Quadra 900 running A/UX. The obscurity is also hastened by hardware it runs on often never being intended for the at home market. The only mainstream Mac I can think of capable of running it was the SE/30. It’s “mainstream” in the sense that it appeared in Seinfeld as a prop in Jerry’s apartment for several seasons. Additionally, with it pre-installed on a Macintosh, it would set you back almost US$10,000 in the late 1980s, or about US$25,000 in 2022 money. This was never meant for the average end user! The second reason is the least likely but came to mind: Doom sort of can run on A/UX already. When I say “sort of”, I am referring to A/UX’s Finder implementation which gives a System 7.0.1 environment. The caveat here is that Doom requires System 7.1, but with a few hacks and tweaks, you can run a later version of the system software albeit with the loss of certain components which makes A/UX itself useful alongside Mac software. My Quadra’s processor while sluggish should not be a problem in running this game I must add, but these older CPUs are single-threaded and can only do much at a time. Doom may seem like a really simple game by modern standards (and it is really a glorified 2D one), but it was cutting edge when it came out in the 1990s. Overall, because of its obscurity and hardware requirements plus emulation capable of running the OS still in its infancy (Shoebill and QEMU are the only options as of this writing), it is likely that my hobbyist exposure plus my love of Doom finally led to an attempt to build the game to run on the platform. The help I received when I streamed my porting attempts definitely made this possible as well, so it was not a solo effort I must admit. Up until this point, my knowledge of any operating system development was limited to Linux, macOS, and Windows, but I guess I can now say I know a little bit about AT&amp;amp;T System V and its A/UX variant. Where can I get this? The source code is available on my GitHub and a compiled binary is available there too. I have no intention to update this further beyond maybe a few tweaks to make it more playable. If you wish to make changes on your own, feel free to fork it or just send me pull requests. Make sure to read the README before compiling as there are a few steps you might need to take in order to get it up and running. I have no idea if the emulators capable of running A/UX can even run this game and I have even less of a clue whether you can run this on anything earlier than version 3.1.1 of the operating system. I have the two streams where I worked on it archived on YouTube (June 5th and June 6th were their recordings), but do give me a follow on Twitch as well as I stream speedrunning, visual novel games, and occasionally stuff like this.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Thoughts on Ace Attorney — the original game trilogy and anime series</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/03/14/thoughts-on-ace-attorney-the-original-game-trilogy-and-anime-series/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Ace Attorney — the original game trilogy and anime series" />
      
      <published>2022-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/03/14/thoughts-on-ace-attorney---the-original-game-trilogy-and-anime-series</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/03/14/thoughts-on-ace-attorney-the-original-game-trilogy-and-anime-series/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hey! Spoilers ahead! This is your only warning! If you have not watched the anime or played the original three games, you are going to learn things you might not want to know yet! I ended up going into a synopsis over an important aspect of the trilogy’s backstory and that will 100% spoil things for you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime around Christmas, the Phoenix Wright Ace Attorney series was on sale. On a whim I opted to buy it with zero expectation that I’d personally enjoy playing it, but I figured that at CA$20, even a single play through of one or two cases would be its money’s worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1m-pPnjHyBMT49_8Jqg3cBw_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a lot of remarks about how painful aspects of the game were and yet I still wanted more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later and 100+ hours of streaming the trilogy on Twitch — with one stream lasting nearly 13-hours for a single case — I have labeled myself as a “fangirl” of this genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also determined to finish this game before &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamesdonequick.com/framefatales&quot;&gt;Frost Fatales&lt;/a&gt;, as I intended to binge watch the anime series during my travel to and from the event — of both which the event and the watching were successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have thoughts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why did I become so engrossed?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to working in security engineering, I worked in digital forensics incident response (DFIR), which taught me a lot about evidence handling, chain of custody, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a lawyer friend, I was given a reality check on how civil and criminal matters in the American context do differ greatly (my focus was primarily in the former), but it never stopped me from looking at everything I did from the point of view of my former work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the completely bizarre way a lawyer must conduct their own investigation and how evidence is presented in court with it sometimes being modified by the prosecution on the fly, the dialogue and storytelling is paced fairly well and throughout the games you discover how incidents from early on matter in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best example of how it all ties together is in the third game, &lt;em&gt;Phoenix Wright: Ace Attorney — Trials and Tribulations, y&lt;/em&gt;ou start a case as Mia Fey, Phoenix’s mentor who an integral and supportive character in the series despite her being deceased. Phoenix himself (who is not yet a lawyer as it is set five year in the past) is accused of the murder of a pharmacy student who was conveniently the ex-boyfriend of Phoenix’s girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story, entitled &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Beginnings&lt;/em&gt;, and the outcome of the case is extremely important to the final game despite being just the tutorial. In the first two games, the tutorial is not as important to the overarching story (the second game’s tutorial is important to the third game weirdly), but here it completely cements it as pivotal to how the whole game will turn out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My field of work and the intense story writing is what really drew me in overall. It’s rather impressive that a game that frustrates me due to its lack of due process and terrifying evidence handling, that it pulls me in due to its excellent story writing and character development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prosecutors Miles Edgeworth and Fransiska von Karma and to a certain extent, Larry Butz are great characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;I hate the circus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And staying on frustrations, the second game, &lt;em&gt;Phoenix Wright: Ace Attorney — Justice for All&lt;/em&gt;, has one of the most frustrating stories and yet the whole game is important to play. The first game could and did stand on its own, but when it was rereleased for the Nintendo DS (originally it was on the Game Boy Advance), an additional case was added to help tie it all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this game’s third story, &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Big Top&lt;/em&gt;, we are introduced to the Berry Big Circus (get it?) and its David Bowie-esque magician, Maximillion Galactica who has a personality so big that it literally swallows up the rest of the circus cast. As per usual, he has been accused of murder of his boss and circus ringleader, Russell Berry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1lLzLZBDL_8m6mkKKmxZT4w_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has played the third case of the second game knows the circus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems with this case are vast and are hard to pin down, so let’s start with its awful music. Despite playing the HD release on the Nintendo Switch, the music pierced into my ears, literally having me state on stream that I wished that my hearing impairment were worse than it already is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referencing back to the bonus case added to the first game, it too had music I could not stand, but it never inflicted the horrible pain that this story gave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then we have the characters and boy did I ever just not like any of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have Regina, the ringleader’s daughter and tamer. She’s 16-years old and is completely naive to her father’s death, suggesting that he is not gone but simply a star in the night’s sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her behaviour implies that she has little education and is completely enamoured with the attention she gets. How she handles the threat against her life and her approach to practical jokes suggests how oblivious she is to the happenings around her. She consistently demonstrated throughout the case an inability to perform any level of critical thinking. She deserves so much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a ventriloquist, Benjamin, who cannot speak coherently without the aide of his puppet, Trilo. You cannot get anything out of Ben without having to deal with Trilo’s behaviour and it becomes infuriating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse, Ben, who is 31, has an engagement ring for Regina, who is nearly half his age. It’s just outright gross and I was really hoping that he was the murderer, but then the game managed to find a worse outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the accused, Max and is aged 22, who is just obnoxious and honestly probably the least frustrating because despite his big ego, you learn that he has a facade up to hide the fact he is from a lower class. He too wants to form a romantic relationship with Regina — please stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His redeeming factor is that while he has disputes with the rest of the cast, he does want what is best for the circus as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s Moe, a late-30s, divorced clown who ends up being the most reasonable character, but his jokes and puns are frustrating. He along with the previous led me to state that despite my prison abolishionism stance, I wanted everyone jailed because it was the best overall option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally the murderer and boy did I ever hate this reveal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first part of the trial, we return to investigate at the circus and we’re introduced to Acro, who is a former acrobat (get it?) and is presently confined to a wheelchair because of an injury. The paralysis-inducing injury was caused by him intervening in an attack on his younger brother by a lion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learn that the lion had injured Acro’s brother, Bat (ugh?), leaving him in a coma. The lion was then shot by Russell. It was revealed that Regina had as a joke gifted Bat a handkerchief laced with pepper, which resulted in the lion sneezing as Bat playfully placed his head in the animal’s mouth to impress the girl (also Bat is 22) all the while wearing the gift he had just received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1Y8oNlCcvxWGam4coq1rzOg_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case had me audibly complaining about every character presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coma Bat was in and his own paralysis left Acro extremely bitter towards Regina, who he intended to seek revenge on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, when Acro decided to take out his revenge on Regina, the letter he had slipped into her clothes as she came to deliver him food never actually made it to her. She did find it, but her naivety led her to just stick it up in the cafeteria for someone else to find. This caused her father to discover it and when he followed the instructions, he died from the dropping of a jade stone or copper lifesize bust resembling Max atop of his head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we get into the ableism nonsense. The bust made its way to Acro’s room via his monkey, Money. This room is on the second floor of the circus dormitories, which is screwed up because this means that Acro is stuck up there with no ability to get down. Downstairs from him is Moe, which then led me to wonder why the hell he didn’t offer to swap room — perhaps this was offered and one’s proudness was in the way, but it’s still messed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, for story purposes, Acro had the bust tied to a rope from the second floor and dropped it atop of the ringleader, who he presumed to be Regina. He had no clue that he was murdering his boss, who he claimed to be a father figure in his life, despite the fact that the man kept him upstairs for months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game decides to dial this up further: the bust is missing. The prosecution and Phoenix himself cannot find the thing. Where is it? How could it go missing? It’s so massive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is the answer: Acro is called to be a witness and you’re compelled to call him out on the bust. Phoenix proudly announces that the bust is in the courtroom and is is literally contained within Acro’s wheelchair, hidden beneath a blanket covering his legs. Acro is revealed to be the murderer and you’re just left completely angry that this is where the game went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it is revealed that Moe is the most reasonable of the cast, but it is hard to recognize this because you spent the whole time angry with everyone either because of the game’s ableism, the negligence toward’s Regina’s intellectual development, or the absurd number of older men being romantically interested in a teenaged girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend, Aura pointed out early on that she liked Moe the most due to his reasonable-ness. While I agree with her wholeheartedly, this case is engrained my mind negatively for so many reasons and consequently became a low point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Kurain village, mysticism, and the Feys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This by far is what redeems &lt;em&gt;Justice for All&lt;/em&gt; and is what really drives what happens in the second and third game. I’m going to recount what happens so I am sorry for this part being long. The story very much cemented my thoughts and feelings on all three games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mia Fey is introduced to us in the first game, but she dies in the second story, &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Sisters&lt;/em&gt;, who is found murdered in her office first by her sister, Maya, and then by Phoenix himself. Maya is then accused of murder because she was first to the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly, this case and the handling of electronic data was what started to really draw me in because chain of custody definitely is not a strong suit of these games, but I digress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, we learn of the Kurain channelling method. This permits Maya to channel her sister, Mia who then assists Phoenix with helping reveal the murderer and win the case for Maya. Mia then tells Phoenix that he should watch over her sister, who then plays a role in all the games, channeling Mia numerous times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She does not appear in the bonus story, &lt;em&gt;Rise from the Ashes&lt;/em&gt;, as she had returned back to her home village at the end of the previous story — hence why the story exists to tie things together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where it really starts to matter with the Fey family is when we’re introduced to Maya’s aunt, Morgan, and her 8-year old cousin, Pearl in the second game’s second story, &lt;em&gt;Reunion and Turnabout.&lt;/em&gt; This story discusses the abilities of the Fey family to channel the deceased into the real world, a skill that both Maya and most importantly for this story, Pearl possess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maya is accused of murder because she supposedly channels someone who was killed due to the actions of her client, who himself was found dead. The story reveals the internal politics of the Fey family, as Maya is from the main branch and as a result is the one to inherit the leadership of the Kurain method as her mother has been missing for long enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pearl is important to this overarching story and also provides us with a game mechanic that while I am not fond of, becomes rather important for progressing through. You’re given a ‘magatama’, which is a special mystical stone you can present as a way to break through someone’s bluffs or lies with evidence to reveal the truth and progress the story — the game gives a visual clue to use the stone through the appearance of “psyche locks”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Maya has been once again accused of murder, you presume that you’ve lost Mia but nope, it turns out that Pearl herself is able to channel too and you work with Mia this way. Pearl’s abilities matching that of Maya is what is driving the politics around the village and Fey family, which becomes extremely important through game 2 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn’t mention about Maya or Pearl channeling Mia is that when they do so, they also channel the appearance of whoever it is. This means that Mia will appear in Maya or Pearl’s clothing, but also ages the body in a way that while with Maya is not unnerving. It becomes extremely so with Pearl since she’s instantly becoming a 27-year old woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s less troubling to me with Maya, who is 17, but Pearl is 8 so yeah. At least Phoenix always saw Mia as a mentor and nothing more, but still. What we learn in the third game provides some level of comfort here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any event, it is revealed that Morgan helped set up the murder through the help of someone seeking revenge over an unrelated matter. It is revealed that Maya never channeled the person the client wanted because the person who he thought was dead wasn’t!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She actually faked her death in a car accident with her sister being the casualty. The injuries endured required facial reconstruction surgery and she used that as an opportunity to take on her sister’s identity right down to her physical appearance. When this is revealed, it’s a fun plot twist, but it results in Maya’s acquittal and Morgan being placed in prison due to her participation in the crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story becomes important and the game makes it apparent at the end of the case, but we don’t come back to the topic until the third game, which opens up with the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Memories&lt;/em&gt;, which is where Phoenix and Mia meet. We are introduced to Phoenix’s ex-girlfriend, Dhalia Hawthorne, who is then revealed to be the murderer in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoenix reveals his desire to become a lawyer, but is adamant about the person Dhalia was to him and the sort of person she is, giving the impression that he is naive about the people around him. With this in mind, Dahlia becomes important despite being dead by the time we get to the last two cases of the third game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second last case, &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Beginnings&lt;/em&gt; involves Dahlia, her sister, Valerie; and her “tutor”, Terry — who seems to be modelled on a certain John Steinbeck character — in a fake kidnapping plot resulting in Terry being accused of murder of Valerie, who herself is a police officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many things are revealed, but importantly it shows that Dhalia has been engaged in shenanigans since she was 14-years old, including seducing a 25-year old “tutor” into being an accessory to everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While as unnerving as we saw in &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Big Top&lt;/em&gt;, it didn’t force matter more than suggestion and instead we witnessed Terry commit suicide on the stand using a poison given to him from Dhalia. This poison becomes important to the backstory behind the game’s main prosecutor, Godot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case is left with Dahlia under suspicion, but Terry is dead and the prosecution is fine with remaining with him accused. We’ve dealt with Dahlia twice now and now we’re going into the final case, &lt;em&gt;Bridge to the Turnabout.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things about the Kurain channeling method and who is to lead it is that May and Mia’s mother is still leader despite having been missing for almost two decades — the reasons for why are revealed in the first game’s fourth story, &lt;em&gt;Turnabout Goodbyes.&lt;/em&gt; Time has passed and it is now required for Maya to begin the process to assume leadership&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We travel to a temple and meet new characters including Elise Deauxnim, who is this up and coming children’s story author and is Pearl is absolutely enamoured with. Also, we meet some other characters, including someone named Iris who looks the same as Dahlia with just a different hair colour. She doesn’t have the same cold demeanour though?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This of course had me on edge because she was found guilty of murder and the game makes it clear that execution soon follows. Has Dahlia escaped death row and has escaped from prison? What is going on? I was pretty terrified of where things were going because this was the last case and we were getting some extreme concentrations of coincidences and occurrences simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then Elise is suddenly found murdered! Then we discover that the rope bridge to the building where Maya is has somehow caught fire (and oh boy it is the same bridge as the previous story), Pearl is missing, and now Phoenix has been swept away by a fast moving current below the bridge because he wanted to rescue Maya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1jStCIdJ5hWXecx471_Ec9g_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so relieved when there was a murder. It’s incredibly messed up for me to type that statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breaking of tension here was incredible and while we are fortunate to learn that Phoenix has been rescued and is alright, his arch-rival and long-time friend, Edgeworth has been tasked to defend Iris at Phoenix’s request. It is confusing because isn’t Iris just Dahlia?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The part of Edgeworth playing defence attorney as opposed to prosecutor is a strange but enjoyable change and he discovers what it is like to play the role Wright has had for so long. We do eventually learn that Dahlia was in fact executed just recently, so who the hell is Iris?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We endure a trial where Edgeworth and his adopted sister and fellow prosecutor, von Karma face off, with the day ending with no verdict, so now we’re to move forward and figure out what has happened to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridge has been given a temporary fix and we run into Pearl (phew) and strangely Godot, who did not show up for the first portion of the trial but will for the second because Phoenix is now out of hospital. However, where is Maya? We did briefly lose Iris, but now she’s back and we’re trying to unlock a chamber that suddenly went from having a single lock to multiples. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we perform some investigations and at some point it is revealed that Elise is infact Misty Fey, Maya and Mia’s mother and Morgan’s sister. Oh yeah. Morgan is still around and it seems that Pearl has been visiting her in prison. We also learn that Dahlia has been visiting Morgan in prison. Oh yeah. We also learn that Dahlia is Morgan’s daughter. Oh yeah. We also learn that Iris is Dahlia’s twin sister, which means that we have our answer to who the hell Iris is — phew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is of course a trope that gets overplayed, but with the whole spirit channeling we’ve dealt with for the past three games, it actually isn’t that bad here and in my opinion works well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who murdered Misty? Larry’s art (oh yeah he’s an artist now and has assumed the last name “Deauxnim”) suggests that she flew across the bridge while it was ablaze — but that is impossible, right? How did Iris do this if she was found on the other side and the bridge was on fire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the big reveal comes in: we’re in court and we’re trying to figure out Iris’ innocence and Phoenix is now facing off against Godot. It finally dawns upon him: Maya is not missing and the murderer is in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/15usXRzU0H8Do0F6X28c5cg_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I have been saying for the past three hours that Dahlia is not dead” (hours pass) “well, okay, this makes more sense now, but I am still sort of right!!!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where is Maya? Simple: she is right here and is channeling Dahlia. But why would she do that? Does that mean that Maya killed her own mother? Well, it is pointed out that Maya reached out to her sister in a panic and Mia suggested she channel Dahlia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirits are not aware of who they’re being channeled by (unless a clue is left in the physical world such as Maya did by leaving a note asking for Mia’s help) and has assumed that Maya was so distraught from having killed her mother that she committed suicide that it was in fact Pearl channeling her since it was what was arranged between her and Morgan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But surprise for Dahlia! Mia is right next to Phoenix in court and she is being channeled by her step-sister, Pearl. This leaves Dahlia confused which then reveals that it is Maya! Dahlia disappears and now we’re left with Maya having to testify to what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Godot had killed Misty in an attempt to save Maya. Misty on purpose channeled Dahlia and was working with Godot in order to protect Maya in the first place. Dahlia had no clue to what had happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Godot is then revealed to be Diego Armando, a defence lawyer and former love interest of Mia who held a grudge against Wright for not stopping her being murdered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iris is found to just be the receiver of the body of Misty and wasn’t actually the murderer — at worst she desecrated a body, which is oddly similar to the game 2 story, &lt;em&gt;Farewell, My Turnabout&lt;/em&gt;. Iris would blindly follow her sister’s wishes and did so because she felt that she had to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also revealed that Diego was poisoned by Dahlia in the same way that Terry had, but managed to survive albeit with a five-year long coma and severe damage to his nervous system. This resulted in him requiring the use of goggles to aide in his vision. Because of their glowing red in the dark, it resulted in a clue Maya gave in her testimony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maya is saved, Dahlia is eternally damned to know she failed to do what she sought out to do, and Godot consumed four dozen cups of coffee in two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the Dahlia Phoenix thought he was dating was actually Iris and Iris was in fact love with Phoenix, so there’s that reveal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The anime tries so hard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about the above is that what I described is really just the surface of the whole game’s story mechanics and imagination. I honestly am not giving it enough justice in how I describe the events as I haven’t talked about the backstory of Miles Edgeworth and Larry Butz in any detail. Their relationship with Phoenix is rather interesting and that is where I think the anime is a bit stronger than the game despite overall being weaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Ace Attorney&lt;/em&gt; anime series largely sticks to the stories from the original trilogy for the most part save for excluding the bonus case from the first game, the addition of some backstory (of which I feel is important and missing from the game), a case on a train that wasn’t in the triology, and that the stories are a bit out of order — I don’t think it is consequential however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1Y5yPjHEHZGckA9UvAtFn_g_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The circus is more bearable in the anime than in the game. On purpose, I am only showing Phoenix and Maya because they’re talking to Moe and I don’t want to see Moe again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the pacing in the anime does not match the game, which I feel took a way a bit of the magic that we got in all the games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a few changes that I felt were either not the best or were for the best. I believe that they were done to fix some pacing or to permit the reordering of stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Lotta Hart shows up in the first two games as a pivotal character, but then Larry takes her place as photog during &lt;em&gt;Reunion and Turnabout&lt;/em&gt;, which I think worked because one of my complaints of the second game was a lack of him — yes, I did miss the guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maggey Byrde from game 2’s first case, &lt;em&gt;The Lost Turnabout&lt;/em&gt; should have been left in sequence in order to provide pacing for the follow up case from game 3’s, &lt;em&gt;Recipe for a Turnabout&lt;/em&gt;. Why I found this disjointing is simply because game 2’s last case, &lt;em&gt;Farewell, My Turnabout&lt;/em&gt; was made the first season’s finale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the anime really shines on the backstory behind Larry, Miles, and Phoenix. Phoenix credits his being a defence attorney because of Edgeworth coming to his aide and while the game spends some time giving details on their backstory, they really rope it in better in the TV series. It really is what makes the anime compelling to watch even if the pacing is out of whack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What is next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see all of my play-throughs of the trilogy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JrYm_9JvUh8&amp;amp;list=PLrYZeeO9Jfco_kvpAyURWAJwTqQL-2qMn&quot;&gt;they’re up on my YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. They were some of my best streams I feel and they’re also the first that have gotten a lot of people watching recordings of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting tomorrow, Tuesday, March 15th at 5 PM PT, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/katelibc&quot;&gt;I’ll be live on Twitch streaming Great Ace Attorney Adventures&lt;/a&gt;, which I guess is a prequel of sorts. I’m super excited and I hope you all will come watch.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Hey! Spoilers ahead! This is your only warning! If you have not watched the anime or played the original three games, you are going to learn things you might not want to know yet! I ended up going into a synopsis over an important aspect of the trilogy’s backstory and that will 100% spoil things for you. Sometime around Christmas, the Phoenix Wright Ace Attorney series was on sale. On a whim I opted to buy it with zero expectation that I’d personally enjoy playing it, but I figured that at CA$20, even a single play through of one or two cases would be its money’s worth. I made a lot of remarks about how painful aspects of the game were and yet I still wanted more. Three months later and 100+ hours of streaming the trilogy on Twitch — with one stream lasting nearly 13-hours for a single case — I have labeled myself as a “fangirl” of this genre. I was also determined to finish this game before Frost Fatales, as I intended to binge watch the anime series during my travel to and from the event — of both which the event and the watching were successful. So now I have thoughts! Why did I become so engrossed? Prior to working in security engineering, I worked in digital forensics incident response (DFIR), which taught me a lot about evidence handling, chain of custody, and so forth. Thanks to a lawyer friend, I was given a reality check on how civil and criminal matters in the American context do differ greatly (my focus was primarily in the former), but it never stopped me from looking at everything I did from the point of view of my former work. Aside from the completely bizarre way a lawyer must conduct their own investigation and how evidence is presented in court with it sometimes being modified by the prosecution on the fly, the dialogue and storytelling is paced fairly well and throughout the games you discover how incidents from early on matter in the end. I think the best example of how it all ties together is in the third game, Phoenix Wright: Ace Attorney — Trials and Tribulations, you start a case as Mia Fey, Phoenix’s mentor who an integral and supportive character in the series despite her being deceased. Phoenix himself (who is not yet a lawyer as it is set five year in the past) is accused of the murder of a pharmacy student who was conveniently the ex-boyfriend of Phoenix’s girlfriend. This story, entitled Turnabout Beginnings, and the outcome of the case is extremely important to the final game despite being just the tutorial. In the first two games, the tutorial is not as important to the overarching story (the second game’s tutorial is important to the third game weirdly), but here it completely cements it as pivotal to how the whole game will turn out. My field of work and the intense story writing is what really drew me in overall. It’s rather impressive that a game that frustrates me due to its lack of due process and terrifying evidence handling, that it pulls me in due to its excellent story writing and character development. The prosecutors Miles Edgeworth and Fransiska von Karma and to a certain extent, Larry Butz are great characters. I hate the circus And staying on frustrations, the second game, Phoenix Wright: Ace Attorney — Justice for All, has one of the most frustrating stories and yet the whole game is important to play. The first game could and did stand on its own, but when it was rereleased for the Nintendo DS (originally it was on the Game Boy Advance), an additional case was added to help tie it all together. In this game’s third story, Turnabout Big Top, we are introduced to the Berry Big Circus (get it?) and its David Bowie-esque magician, Maximillion Galactica who has a personality so big that it literally swallows up the rest of the circus cast. As per usual, he has been accused of murder of his boss and circus ringleader, Russell Berry. Anyone who has played the third case of the second game knows the circus. The problems with this case are vast and are hard to pin down, so let’s start with its awful music. Despite playing the HD release on the Nintendo Switch, the music pierced into my ears, literally having me state on stream that I wished that my hearing impairment were worse than it already is. Referencing back to the bonus case added to the first game, it too had music I could not stand, but it never inflicted the horrible pain that this story gave. But then we have the characters and boy did I ever just not like any of them. We have Regina, the ringleader’s daughter and tamer. She’s 16-years old and is completely naive to her father’s death, suggesting that he is not gone but simply a star in the night’s sky. Her behaviour implies that she has little education and is completely enamoured with the attention she gets. How she handles the threat against her life and her approach to practical jokes suggests how oblivious she is to the happenings around her. She consistently demonstrated throughout the case an inability to perform any level of critical thinking. She deserves so much better. There’s a ventriloquist, Benjamin, who cannot speak coherently without the aide of his puppet, Trilo. You cannot get anything out of Ben without having to deal with Trilo’s behaviour and it becomes infuriating. To make matters worse, Ben, who is 31, has an engagement ring for Regina, who is nearly half his age. It’s just outright gross and I was really hoping that he was the murderer, but then the game managed to find a worse outcome. We have the accused, Max and is aged 22, who is just obnoxious and honestly probably the least frustrating because despite his big ego, you learn that he has a facade up to hide the fact he is from a lower class. He too wants to form a romantic relationship with Regina — please stop. His redeeming factor is that while he has disputes with the rest of the cast, he does want what is best for the circus as a whole. Then there’s Moe, a late-30s, divorced clown who ends up being the most reasonable character, but his jokes and puns are frustrating. He along with the previous led me to state that despite my prison abolishionism stance, I wanted everyone jailed because it was the best overall option. And finally the murderer and boy did I ever hate this reveal. After the first part of the trial, we return to investigate at the circus and we’re introduced to Acro, who is a former acrobat (get it?) and is presently confined to a wheelchair because of an injury. The paralysis-inducing injury was caused by him intervening in an attack on his younger brother by a lion. We learn that the lion had injured Acro’s brother, Bat (ugh?), leaving him in a coma. The lion was then shot by Russell. It was revealed that Regina had as a joke gifted Bat a handkerchief laced with pepper, which resulted in the lion sneezing as Bat playfully placed his head in the animal’s mouth to impress the girl (also Bat is 22) all the while wearing the gift he had just received. This case had me audibly complaining about every character presented. The coma Bat was in and his own paralysis left Acro extremely bitter towards Regina, who he intended to seek revenge on. Of course, when Acro decided to take out his revenge on Regina, the letter he had slipped into her clothes as she came to deliver him food never actually made it to her. She did find it, but her naivety led her to just stick it up in the cafeteria for someone else to find. This caused her father to discover it and when he followed the instructions, he died from the dropping of a jade stone or copper lifesize bust resembling Max atop of his head. Then we get into the ableism nonsense. The bust made its way to Acro’s room via his monkey, Money. This room is on the second floor of the circus dormitories, which is screwed up because this means that Acro is stuck up there with no ability to get down. Downstairs from him is Moe, which then led me to wonder why the hell he didn’t offer to swap room — perhaps this was offered and one’s proudness was in the way, but it’s still messed up. Of course, for story purposes, Acro had the bust tied to a rope from the second floor and dropped it atop of the ringleader, who he presumed to be Regina. He had no clue that he was murdering his boss, who he claimed to be a father figure in his life, despite the fact that the man kept him upstairs for months. The game decides to dial this up further: the bust is missing. The prosecution and Phoenix himself cannot find the thing. Where is it? How could it go missing? It’s so massive. And this is the answer: Acro is called to be a witness and you’re compelled to call him out on the bust. Phoenix proudly announces that the bust is in the courtroom and is is literally contained within Acro’s wheelchair, hidden beneath a blanket covering his legs. Acro is revealed to be the murderer and you’re just left completely angry that this is where the game went. Finally, it is revealed that Moe is the most reasonable of the cast, but it is hard to recognize this because you spent the whole time angry with everyone either because of the game’s ableism, the negligence toward’s Regina’s intellectual development, or the absurd number of older men being romantically interested in a teenaged girl. My friend, Aura pointed out early on that she liked Moe the most due to his reasonable-ness. While I agree with her wholeheartedly, this case is engrained my mind negatively for so many reasons and consequently became a low point. Kurain village, mysticism, and the Feys This by far is what redeems Justice for All and is what really drives what happens in the second and third game. I’m going to recount what happens so I am sorry for this part being long. The story very much cemented my thoughts and feelings on all three games. Mia Fey is introduced to us in the first game, but she dies in the second story, Turnabout Sisters, who is found murdered in her office first by her sister, Maya, and then by Phoenix himself. Maya is then accused of murder because she was first to the scene. Oddly, this case and the handling of electronic data was what started to really draw me in because chain of custody definitely is not a strong suit of these games, but I digress. In this case, we learn of the Kurain channelling method. This permits Maya to channel her sister, Mia who then assists Phoenix with helping reveal the murderer and win the case for Maya. Mia then tells Phoenix that he should watch over her sister, who then plays a role in all the games, channeling Mia numerous times. She does not appear in the bonus story, Rise from the Ashes, as she had returned back to her home village at the end of the previous story — hence why the story exists to tie things together. Where it really starts to matter with the Fey family is when we’re introduced to Maya’s aunt, Morgan, and her 8-year old cousin, Pearl in the second game’s second story, Reunion and Turnabout. This story discusses the abilities of the Fey family to channel the deceased into the real world, a skill that both Maya and most importantly for this story, Pearl possess. Maya is accused of murder because she supposedly channels someone who was killed due to the actions of her client, who himself was found dead. The story reveals the internal politics of the Fey family, as Maya is from the main branch and as a result is the one to inherit the leadership of the Kurain method as her mother has been missing for long enough. Pearl is important to this overarching story and also provides us with a game mechanic that while I am not fond of, becomes rather important for progressing through. You’re given a ‘magatama’, which is a special mystical stone you can present as a way to break through someone’s bluffs or lies with evidence to reveal the truth and progress the story — the game gives a visual clue to use the stone through the appearance of “psyche locks”. Since Maya has been once again accused of murder, you presume that you’ve lost Mia but nope, it turns out that Pearl herself is able to channel too and you work with Mia this way. Pearl’s abilities matching that of Maya is what is driving the politics around the village and Fey family, which becomes extremely important through game 2 and 3. One thing I didn’t mention about Maya or Pearl channeling Mia is that when they do so, they also channel the appearance of whoever it is. This means that Mia will appear in Maya or Pearl’s clothing, but also ages the body in a way that while with Maya is not unnerving. It becomes extremely so with Pearl since she’s instantly becoming a 27-year old woman. It’s less troubling to me with Maya, who is 17, but Pearl is 8 so yeah. At least Phoenix always saw Mia as a mentor and nothing more, but still. What we learn in the third game provides some level of comfort here. In any event, it is revealed that Morgan helped set up the murder through the help of someone seeking revenge over an unrelated matter. It is revealed that Maya never channeled the person the client wanted because the person who he thought was dead wasn’t! She actually faked her death in a car accident with her sister being the casualty. The injuries endured required facial reconstruction surgery and she used that as an opportunity to take on her sister’s identity right down to her physical appearance. When this is revealed, it’s a fun plot twist, but it results in Maya’s acquittal and Morgan being placed in prison due to her participation in the crime. This story becomes important and the game makes it apparent at the end of the case, but we don’t come back to the topic until the third game, which opens up with the aforementioned Turnabout Memories, which is where Phoenix and Mia meet. We are introduced to Phoenix’s ex-girlfriend, Dhalia Hawthorne, who is then revealed to be the murderer in this case. Phoenix reveals his desire to become a lawyer, but is adamant about the person Dhalia was to him and the sort of person she is, giving the impression that he is naive about the people around him. With this in mind, Dahlia becomes important despite being dead by the time we get to the last two cases of the third game. The second last case, Turnabout Beginnings involves Dahlia, her sister, Valerie; and her “tutor”, Terry — who seems to be modelled on a certain John Steinbeck character — in a fake kidnapping plot resulting in Terry being accused of murder of Valerie, who herself is a police officer. So many things are revealed, but importantly it shows that Dhalia has been engaged in shenanigans since she was 14-years old, including seducing a 25-year old “tutor” into being an accessory to everything. While as unnerving as we saw in Turnabout Big Top, it didn’t force matter more than suggestion and instead we witnessed Terry commit suicide on the stand using a poison given to him from Dhalia. This poison becomes important to the backstory behind the game’s main prosecutor, Godot. The case is left with Dahlia under suspicion, but Terry is dead and the prosecution is fine with remaining with him accused. We’ve dealt with Dahlia twice now and now we’re going into the final case, Bridge to the Turnabout. One of the things about the Kurain channeling method and who is to lead it is that May and Mia’s mother is still leader despite having been missing for almost two decades — the reasons for why are revealed in the first game’s fourth story, Turnabout Goodbyes. Time has passed and it is now required for Maya to begin the process to assume leadership We travel to a temple and meet new characters including Elise Deauxnim, who is this up and coming children’s story author and is Pearl is absolutely enamoured with. Also, we meet some other characters, including someone named Iris who looks the same as Dahlia with just a different hair colour. She doesn’t have the same cold demeanour though? This of course had me on edge because she was found guilty of murder and the game makes it clear that execution soon follows. Has Dahlia escaped death row and has escaped from prison? What is going on? I was pretty terrified of where things were going because this was the last case and we were getting some extreme concentrations of coincidences and occurrences simultaneously. And then Elise is suddenly found murdered! Then we discover that the rope bridge to the building where Maya is has somehow caught fire (and oh boy it is the same bridge as the previous story), Pearl is missing, and now Phoenix has been swept away by a fast moving current below the bridge because he wanted to rescue Maya. I was so relieved when there was a murder. It’s incredibly messed up for me to type that statement. The breaking of tension here was incredible and while we are fortunate to learn that Phoenix has been rescued and is alright, his arch-rival and long-time friend, Edgeworth has been tasked to defend Iris at Phoenix’s request. It is confusing because isn’t Iris just Dahlia? The part of Edgeworth playing defence attorney as opposed to prosecutor is a strange but enjoyable change and he discovers what it is like to play the role Wright has had for so long. We do eventually learn that Dahlia was in fact executed just recently, so who the hell is Iris? We endure a trial where Edgeworth and his adopted sister and fellow prosecutor, von Karma face off, with the day ending with no verdict, so now we’re to move forward and figure out what has happened to everyone. The bridge has been given a temporary fix and we run into Pearl (phew) and strangely Godot, who did not show up for the first portion of the trial but will for the second because Phoenix is now out of hospital. However, where is Maya? We did briefly lose Iris, but now she’s back and we’re trying to unlock a chamber that suddenly went from having a single lock to multiples. Why? Eventually we perform some investigations and at some point it is revealed that Elise is infact Misty Fey, Maya and Mia’s mother and Morgan’s sister. Oh yeah. Morgan is still around and it seems that Pearl has been visiting her in prison. We also learn that Dahlia has been visiting Morgan in prison. Oh yeah. We also learn that Dahlia is Morgan’s daughter. Oh yeah. We also learn that Iris is Dahlia’s twin sister, which means that we have our answer to who the hell Iris is — phew. This is of course a trope that gets overplayed, but with the whole spirit channeling we’ve dealt with for the past three games, it actually isn’t that bad here and in my opinion works well. So who murdered Misty? Larry’s art (oh yeah he’s an artist now and has assumed the last name “Deauxnim”) suggests that she flew across the bridge while it was ablaze — but that is impossible, right? How did Iris do this if she was found on the other side and the bridge was on fire? This is where the big reveal comes in: we’re in court and we’re trying to figure out Iris’ innocence and Phoenix is now facing off against Godot. It finally dawns upon him: Maya is not missing and the murderer is in court. “I have been saying for the past three hours that Dahlia is not dead” (hours pass) “well, okay, this makes more sense now, but I am still sort of right!!!” Where is Maya? Simple: she is right here and is channeling Dahlia. But why would she do that? Does that mean that Maya killed her own mother? Well, it is pointed out that Maya reached out to her sister in a panic and Mia suggested she channel Dahlia. The spirits are not aware of who they’re being channeled by (unless a clue is left in the physical world such as Maya did by leaving a note asking for Mia’s help) and has assumed that Maya was so distraught from having killed her mother that she committed suicide that it was in fact Pearl channeling her since it was what was arranged between her and Morgan. But surprise for Dahlia! Mia is right next to Phoenix in court and she is being channeled by her step-sister, Pearl. This leaves Dahlia confused which then reveals that it is Maya! Dahlia disappears and now we’re left with Maya having to testify to what happened. It turns out that Godot had killed Misty in an attempt to save Maya. Misty on purpose channeled Dahlia and was working with Godot in order to protect Maya in the first place. Dahlia had no clue to what had happened. Godot is then revealed to be Diego Armando, a defence lawyer and former love interest of Mia who held a grudge against Wright for not stopping her being murdered. Iris is found to just be the receiver of the body of Misty and wasn’t actually the murderer — at worst she desecrated a body, which is oddly similar to the game 2 story, Farewell, My Turnabout. Iris would blindly follow her sister’s wishes and did so because she felt that she had to. It’s also revealed that Diego was poisoned by Dahlia in the same way that Terry had, but managed to survive albeit with a five-year long coma and severe damage to his nervous system. This resulted in him requiring the use of goggles to aide in his vision. Because of their glowing red in the dark, it resulted in a clue Maya gave in her testimony. Maya is saved, Dahlia is eternally damned to know she failed to do what she sought out to do, and Godot consumed four dozen cups of coffee in two days. Also the Dahlia Phoenix thought he was dating was actually Iris and Iris was in fact love with Phoenix, so there’s that reveal. The anime tries so hard The thing about the above is that what I described is really just the surface of the whole game’s story mechanics and imagination. I honestly am not giving it enough justice in how I describe the events as I haven’t talked about the backstory of Miles Edgeworth and Larry Butz in any detail. Their relationship with Phoenix is rather interesting and that is where I think the anime is a bit stronger than the game despite overall being weaker. The Ace Attorney anime series largely sticks to the stories from the original trilogy for the most part save for excluding the bonus case from the first game, the addition of some backstory (of which I feel is important and missing from the game), a case on a train that wasn’t in the triology, and that the stories are a bit out of order — I don’t think it is consequential however. The circus is more bearable in the anime than in the game. On purpose, I am only showing Phoenix and Maya because they’re talking to Moe and I don’t want to see Moe again. Additionally, the pacing in the anime does not match the game, which I feel took a way a bit of the magic that we got in all the games. There were a few changes that I felt were either not the best or were for the best. I believe that they were done to fix some pacing or to permit the reordering of stories. For example, Lotta Hart shows up in the first two games as a pivotal character, but then Larry takes her place as photog during Reunion and Turnabout, which I think worked because one of my complaints of the second game was a lack of him — yes, I did miss the guy. Maggey Byrde from game 2’s first case, The Lost Turnabout should have been left in sequence in order to provide pacing for the follow up case from game 3’s, Recipe for a Turnabout. Why I found this disjointing is simply because game 2’s last case, Farewell, My Turnabout was made the first season’s finale. However, the anime really shines on the backstory behind Larry, Miles, and Phoenix. Phoenix credits his being a defence attorney because of Edgeworth coming to his aide and while the game spends some time giving details on their backstory, they really rope it in better in the TV series. It really is what makes the anime compelling to watch even if the pacing is out of whack. What is next? If you want to see all of my play-throughs of the trilogy, they’re up on my YouTube. They were some of my best streams I feel and they’re also the first that have gotten a lot of people watching recordings of. Starting tomorrow, Tuesday, March 15th at 5 PM PT, I’ll be live on Twitch streaming Great Ace Attorney Adventures, which I guess is a prequel of sorts. I’m super excited and I hope you all will come watch.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Adventures with an 11,000 kilometre-long Game Boy Advance link</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/02/03/adventures-with-an-11-000-kilometre-long-game-boy-advance-link/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adventures with an 11,000 kilometre-long Game Boy Advance link" />
      
      <published>2022-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/02/03/adventures-with-an-11-000-kilometre-long-game-boy-advance-link</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/02/03/adventures-with-an-11-000-kilometre-long-game-boy-advance-link/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I lamented a lot growing up was an inability to find anyone else to do Game Boy link cable games with. I had a few games which would work with the setup, but very few of my friends had Game Boys themselves and when my younger brother received a Game Boy Pocket (I had the black-coloured original), &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Game_Link_Cable&quot;&gt;it used a different cable all together&lt;/a&gt;, making it impossible for us to play Pokémon together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Game Boy was always on its own little island, never to see any real interaction any other device. It wasn’t until I was much older that I would have the ability to hook it up with other Game Boys since I now own a Game Boy Advance (GBA), Game Boy Player, and Super Game Boy 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But everything is online now and starting with the handheld’s successor, the Nintendo DS: it’s also wireless. There are a lot of gems for the Game Boy out there which relied on this cable that have since become largely forgotten or at least cannot have the full extent of their capabilities realized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The GameCube and Game Boy Advance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the features of the GameCube was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GameCube_%E2%80%93_Game_Boy_Advance_link_cable&quot;&gt;the ability to attach to a GBA via a controller port&lt;/a&gt;. This wasn’t meant to output from a handheld to a TV necessarily (such as with the Super Game Boy on the Super Nintendo), but instead to act as an alternate controller or to transfer content between. This same cable also works on Wii consoles with the appropriate controller ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1biEqjKPLVVy6BPn4aH8mQA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My rather beat-up GameCube attached to a Game Boy Advance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other benefit of this cable is when using the Game Boy Player, you can use the GBA as a controller instead of the awkwardly-shaped one provided with the console. And if you want to go further, you can also attach the cable to another GameCube if you want to make use of the Player on there instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1CP7mcsRxMfHKIsI5k1FRaA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As weird as this looks, it’s entirely possible to use your Wii and GameCube this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1d9KzsC1W4sHm32hHWYZy2w_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can go all “chaotic evil” and use this configuration, which too works, but not for the purposes of I am discussing here — I just thought it was neat to share! Two friends of mine gave me a SGB2 after returning from Japan and it’s a far better device than the original Super Game Boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the features of the GBA is the ability to load software on it without having to insert a cartridge. This made the handheld rather powerful as a game loaded on a GameCube could load content on to a handheld without additional copies of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was taken advantage of games such as PacMan Vs., Final Fantasy Crystal Chronicles, and importantly for this article, The Legend of Zelda: Four Swords Adventure. All of these games required the use of a GBA to be attached for multiplayer action and acted a lot like what you’d see in some Wii U games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this required you to have multiple GBA handhelds, the cables themselves (sold separately), and the appropriate copy of the GameCube game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A ridiculous dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the consequences of the ongoing pandemic is the inability to not only safely play some games in the comfort of our own homes, but to travel to see each other when we have shared interests. I’ve been wanting to play one of the aforementioned games with a few friends, but safety is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on and off I’ve been thinking about just playing these games over the Internet. It was more or less an idle thought in 2020, but then in early 2021, someone &lt;a href=&quot;https://stacksmashing.gumroad.com/l/gb-link&quot;&gt;released an adapter&lt;/a&gt; which allowed you to make use of a Raspberry Pi Pico to allow a desktop computer to interface with a link cable. I quickly ordered one and assembled it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1mBkQoK2tVo7PKO4yF5v-gg_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. This doesn’t work. Yes. That is my Game Boy from childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s now no reason that physically a GameCube couldn’t attach to the Internet if I had at least three of these USB adapters attached to the console with three of those appropriate link cables, and then three other people with GBAs with the same adapters attached to their PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is where the problems started: it required everyone to have the hardware. Unfortunately, that wasn’t going to be the only issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adapter itself was intended purely to trade Pokémon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gbplay.io/2021/05/10/An-8-Bit-Idea_The-Internet-of-Game-Boys.html&quot;&gt;which itself should work even with the latency the Internet creates&lt;/a&gt;. It was designed around the idea that it should be fine for pure Game Boy to Game Boy connectivity, which is forgiving due to how the protocol is supposed to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since the link protocol is synchronous and bits are sent and received simultaneously, that means the master device requires the slave to send its response at a rate equal to the clock speed. In non-Game Boy Color mode, the master Game Boy supplies an 8KHz clock (data transfer speed of 1KB/s). This means that there is only a ~120μs window to respond! The Game Boy Color can operate at even higher speeds. No internet connection could possibly satisfy this latency requirement. However, the slave device has no such constraints. It just responds when it receives data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it doesn’t appear that this is the case with the GBA. Based on what I am reading in some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.akkit.org/info/gbatek.htm#gbacommunicationports&quot;&gt;excellent documentation&lt;/a&gt;, the clock rate is even tighter with its tolerances (256 KHz to 2 MHz for the GBA as opposed to the original Game Boy’s 8 KHz). As a result, the hardware is unlikely to accept being a GameCube controller once you are of significant distance, which in the GBA’s case is more than a few metres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe the hardware being a problem is a non-issue. What if we just scrapped the hardware idea and do this using software instead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luck would have it that a few months after the USB adapter was released, the team behind the GameCube (and Wii) emulator, Dolphin announced a new feature: &lt;a href=&quot;https://dolphin-emu.org/blog/2021/07/21/integrated-gba/&quot;&gt;Game Boy Advance netplay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was no small feat for the team, but they’re also known for being rather meticulous and talented with their software. It wasn’t fool-proof and was rife with problems as evident from this excerpt from their blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These games in particular loved to spam tons of commands, sometimes sending over 200 commands a frame. This exposed a rather serious flaw in the TCP GBA protocol. Namely, they could get tripped up if they received a command while they were still emulating forward to catch up to the point from the previous command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I casually brought up in the fall of that year that I wanted to do this, someone linked the above blog piece, which then led to some organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Getting a crew together&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually my friends, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/authorblues&quot;&gt;authorblues&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/callmewuest&quot;&gt;tinahacks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aetyate&quot;&gt;Aetyate&lt;/a&gt;, and I got together to go over playing this game online. We kept testing brief as we wanted to play the chosen game mostly obscured from us aside from “does it work”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we were assured, we set up a night to play and thus &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Four_Swords_Adventures&quot;&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Four Swords Adventures&lt;/a&gt; was being played on Twitch with all four Game Boy Advance displays on stream alongside the GameCube game itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1gGnKQnz084ShaEcJTTbdgQ_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to go back and forth between the GameCube screen and the Game Boy Advance you’re playing on in order to complete this game in multiplayer. In single player mode, this is not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Aetyate and authorblues are in the eastern United States, tinahacks herself is in Finland. With my being in Vancouver, we effectively had two 4,000 KM (2,500 mi) connections and an 11,000 KM (6,800 mi) one going to my PC, playing a game which originally used a two metre (6 ft) cable itself — these distances are approximations and not based on the actual connections between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single button press would find itself travelling 15,000 KM (9,300 mi) one-way, meaning that we’re approaching at least 3/4ths of the circumference of the whole planet considering the nature of of both TCP and the link cable protocols. The emulator was required to do this in order to keep everything in sync and consequently we had to endure somewhere of a 1/5th of a second delay on our individual inputs just to make it manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was possible and we were playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1ORWszohXzW0wOvRsMpL84w_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two people in the eastern United States, one in northern Europe, and myself in Western Canada were about to do something that would have been seen as absurd when the game initially came out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reducing the latency was something I had considered. I looked at options for acquiring a virtual machine with a GPU located somewhere in eastern North America close to fibre links across the Atlantic to Europe, but the costs for such systems have become quite expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, one large cloud computing service was quoting me US$800 for a single month’s use of a machine meeting these requirements. Even with a discount I had available plus US$450 in credits I had with them, it just didn’t seem worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1ejRHQzvvt3WSAZq2EwP96A_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we learnt quick to do was test our controllers by using the battle mode within the game just to make sure that nothing found itself remapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was something another streamer had done in order to host fighting games online and had a great deal of success, but we didn’t feel that the cost was worth it for what we were playing. Four Swords Adventure is an action role playing game and with two streams of this game under our belt, we were feeling that latency would not hinder us too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or so we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;When the lag caught up with us&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latency in Four Swords Adventures was largely manageable for us and often was comical. In fact, the latency was the least of our concerns for the most part as we had other issues to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one of our streams, tinahacks’ copy of Dolphin suddenly ran into problems and started to spew all sorts of errors on her computer. Fortunately, we were not too far past the last save point so we all opted to just restart Dolphin and carry on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/159SGRCsm1gIjskJjPmU_ew_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the game broke, the stream broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On average, I was seeing about 60–80 ms of latency between Aetyate and I, 110–130 ms for authorblues, and unsurprisingly, 180–220 ms for tinahacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the whole 1/5th of a second from earlier comes from. We were restricted by the laws of physics to what options we had available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dolphin includes an adjustable buffer setting in its netplay feature and we can adjust it based on what feels right. I kept it at ‘20’ the whole time as reducing it any further started to introduce audio choppiness and that is just not good “stream content”. It was fine for the first two streams, but towards the middle of our third night of playing the game, it reared its ugly head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game wanted us to walk in-step to get to the other side and failing to do so would result in us having to circle back to where we began on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1lX02ALhpysQKJFFyiOgSkA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking into this square without care will lead to you falling into a pit and having to come around back. You can see Aetyate falling into a pit on the bottom-right with myself and authorblues right — tinahacks is presently dashing across on the far right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically if you run across a pit in a Zelda game, you can use your “Pegasus Boots” item to quickly dart across large gaps. However, the game developers placed what appears to be potato-pineapple hybrids in the way so if you were to dash across, you’d collide with them and then fall down the pit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game requires you to walk parallel to each other in formation in order to keep the platform balanced and then upon approaching the blocked items, simultaneously pull them off of the ground and then toss them. If you can pull off the second part successfully, then the pit is resolved so all we need to worry about is just getting at least one of us across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the current buffer settings, we probably made a dozen and a half if not more attempts. It was starting to look dire as the input latency combined with the latency that a Discord audio call produces made it impossible for us to just get the timing down right. It was beginning to look like this might be the end of this fun experiment until we tried one idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just make the buffer not exist and play the game frame-by-frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You absolutely should watch the video in this tweet to understand how everything went because while we were successful, someone decided to be a “bother” once it was known that we made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each frame we progressed was progress in itself and when we made it to the other side, almost all of us managed to remember to pick up the object on the other end — I inadvertently hit my sword button instead (oops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What proceeded was pure comedy because once one of us successfully got over, another went and attempted to sabotage everything because it was possible to get away with that now and I found myself and that saboteur at the bottom of the pit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this was no longer a problem as now the boots I had put on earlier were now possible as an option across this pit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1nwZy5gRIV8l4r5ymWaiDGQ_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least two of us were on the other side despite someone’s best efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t the only obvious latency problem we had to contend with as a prior boss battle during this stream was proving difficult due to a need to time certain actions, but this was the first time we had to adjust the emulation in order to actually make any meaningful progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a few more streams of this game left with plans for this upcoming Sunday and Tuesday (February 6 and 8, 2022), with the second day being a hopeful completion of what has been a rather fun experience. This will be on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/authorblues&quot;&gt;authorblues’ Twitch channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in watching the past broadcasts, you can view the VODs on Twitch here (I will do my best to update this with the other streams once we are done):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/videos/1283953211&quot;&gt;February 1, 2022 (Part 3)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/videos/1276216366&quot;&gt;January 25, 2022 (Part 2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/videos/1270519533&quot;&gt;January 20, 2022 (Part 1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing our misadventures, we intend to play &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_Crystal_Chronicles_%28video_game%29&quot;&gt;Final Fantasy Crystal Chronicles&lt;/a&gt;, which is another game I have never played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is likely to be after the upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamesdonequick.com/framefatales&quot;&gt;Frost Fatales 2022&lt;/a&gt;, an all-women speedrunning marathon I contribute my spare time to. I hope you’ll check out as we’re raising money for Malala Fund and lots of talented women will show how fast they can play games!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the things I lamented a lot growing up was an inability to find anyone else to do Game Boy link cable games with. I had a few games which would work with the setup, but very few of my friends had Game Boys themselves and when my younger brother received a Game Boy Pocket (I had the black-coloured original), it used a different cable all together, making it impossible for us to play Pokémon together. My Game Boy was always on its own little island, never to see any real interaction any other device. It wasn’t until I was much older that I would have the ability to hook it up with other Game Boys since I now own a Game Boy Advance (GBA), Game Boy Player, and Super Game Boy 2. But everything is online now and starting with the handheld’s successor, the Nintendo DS: it’s also wireless. There are a lot of gems for the Game Boy out there which relied on this cable that have since become largely forgotten or at least cannot have the full extent of their capabilities realized. The GameCube and Game Boy Advance One of the features of the GameCube was the ability to attach to a GBA via a controller port. This wasn’t meant to output from a handheld to a TV necessarily (such as with the Super Game Boy on the Super Nintendo), but instead to act as an alternate controller or to transfer content between. This same cable also works on Wii consoles with the appropriate controller ports. My rather beat-up GameCube attached to a Game Boy Advance One other benefit of this cable is when using the Game Boy Player, you can use the GBA as a controller instead of the awkwardly-shaped one provided with the console. And if you want to go further, you can also attach the cable to another GameCube if you want to make use of the Player on there instead. As weird as this looks, it’s entirely possible to use your Wii and GameCube this way. Or you can go all “chaotic evil” and use this configuration, which too works, but not for the purposes of I am discussing here — I just thought it was neat to share! Two friends of mine gave me a SGB2 after returning from Japan and it’s a far better device than the original Super Game Boy. One of the features of the GBA is the ability to load software on it without having to insert a cartridge. This made the handheld rather powerful as a game loaded on a GameCube could load content on to a handheld without additional copies of software. This was taken advantage of games such as PacMan Vs., Final Fantasy Crystal Chronicles, and importantly for this article, The Legend of Zelda: Four Swords Adventure. All of these games required the use of a GBA to be attached for multiplayer action and acted a lot like what you’d see in some Wii U games. However, this required you to have multiple GBA handhelds, the cables themselves (sold separately), and the appropriate copy of the GameCube game. A ridiculous dream One of the consequences of the ongoing pandemic is the inability to not only safely play some games in the comfort of our own homes, but to travel to see each other when we have shared interests. I’ve been wanting to play one of the aforementioned games with a few friends, but safety is important. So on and off I’ve been thinking about just playing these games over the Internet. It was more or less an idle thought in 2020, but then in early 2021, someone released an adapter which allowed you to make use of a Raspberry Pi Pico to allow a desktop computer to interface with a link cable. I quickly ordered one and assembled it. No. This doesn’t work. Yes. That is my Game Boy from childhood. There’s now no reason that physically a GameCube couldn’t attach to the Internet if I had at least three of these USB adapters attached to the console with three of those appropriate link cables, and then three other people with GBAs with the same adapters attached to their PCs. And that is where the problems started: it required everyone to have the hardware. Unfortunately, that wasn’t going to be the only issue. The adapter itself was intended purely to trade Pokémon, which itself should work even with the latency the Internet creates. It was designed around the idea that it should be fine for pure Game Boy to Game Boy connectivity, which is forgiving due to how the protocol is supposed to work. Since the link protocol is synchronous and bits are sent and received simultaneously, that means the master device requires the slave to send its response at a rate equal to the clock speed. In non-Game Boy Color mode, the master Game Boy supplies an 8KHz clock (data transfer speed of 1KB/s). This means that there is only a ~120μs window to respond! The Game Boy Color can operate at even higher speeds. No internet connection could possibly satisfy this latency requirement. However, the slave device has no such constraints. It just responds when it receives data! Unfortunately, it doesn’t appear that this is the case with the GBA. Based on what I am reading in some excellent documentation, the clock rate is even tighter with its tolerances (256 KHz to 2 MHz for the GBA as opposed to the original Game Boy’s 8 KHz). As a result, the hardware is unlikely to accept being a GameCube controller once you are of significant distance, which in the GBA’s case is more than a few metres. But maybe the hardware being a problem is a non-issue. What if we just scrapped the hardware idea and do this using software instead? Luck would have it that a few months after the USB adapter was released, the team behind the GameCube (and Wii) emulator, Dolphin announced a new feature: Game Boy Advance netplay. This was no small feat for the team, but they’re also known for being rather meticulous and talented with their software. It wasn’t fool-proof and was rife with problems as evident from this excerpt from their blog: These games in particular loved to spam tons of commands, sometimes sending over 200 commands a frame. This exposed a rather serious flaw in the TCP GBA protocol. Namely, they could get tripped up if they received a command while they were still emulating forward to catch up to the point from the previous command. When I casually brought up in the fall of that year that I wanted to do this, someone linked the above blog piece, which then led to some organization. Getting a crew together Eventually my friends, authorblues, tinahacks, Aetyate, and I got together to go over playing this game online. We kept testing brief as we wanted to play the chosen game mostly obscured from us aside from “does it work”. Once we were assured, we set up a night to play and thus The Legend of Zelda: Four Swords Adventures was being played on Twitch with all four Game Boy Advance displays on stream alongside the GameCube game itself. You have to go back and forth between the GameCube screen and the Game Boy Advance you’re playing on in order to complete this game in multiplayer. In single player mode, this is not required. While Aetyate and authorblues are in the eastern United States, tinahacks herself is in Finland. With my being in Vancouver, we effectively had two 4,000 KM (2,500 mi) connections and an 11,000 KM (6,800 mi) one going to my PC, playing a game which originally used a two metre (6 ft) cable itself — these distances are approximations and not based on the actual connections between us. A single button press would find itself travelling 15,000 KM (9,300 mi) one-way, meaning that we’re approaching at least 3/4ths of the circumference of the whole planet considering the nature of of both TCP and the link cable protocols. The emulator was required to do this in order to keep everything in sync and consequently we had to endure somewhere of a 1/5th of a second delay on our individual inputs just to make it manageable. But it was possible and we were playing it. Two people in the eastern United States, one in northern Europe, and myself in Western Canada were about to do something that would have been seen as absurd when the game initially came out Reducing the latency was something I had considered. I looked at options for acquiring a virtual machine with a GPU located somewhere in eastern North America close to fibre links across the Atlantic to Europe, but the costs for such systems have become quite expensive. For example, one large cloud computing service was quoting me US$800 for a single month’s use of a machine meeting these requirements. Even with a discount I had available plus US$450 in credits I had with them, it just didn’t seem worth it. One thing we learnt quick to do was test our controllers by using the battle mode within the game just to make sure that nothing found itself remapped. This was something another streamer had done in order to host fighting games online and had a great deal of success, but we didn’t feel that the cost was worth it for what we were playing. Four Swords Adventure is an action role playing game and with two streams of this game under our belt, we were feeling that latency would not hinder us too much. Or so we thought. When the lag caught up with us The latency in Four Swords Adventures was largely manageable for us and often was comical. In fact, the latency was the least of our concerns for the most part as we had other issues to deal with. During one of our streams, tinahacks’ copy of Dolphin suddenly ran into problems and started to spew all sorts of errors on her computer. Fortunately, we were not too far past the last save point so we all opted to just restart Dolphin and carry on. When the game broke, the stream broke. On average, I was seeing about 60–80 ms of latency between Aetyate and I, 110–130 ms for authorblues, and unsurprisingly, 180–220 ms for tinahacks. This is where the whole 1/5th of a second from earlier comes from. We were restricted by the laws of physics to what options we had available. Dolphin includes an adjustable buffer setting in its netplay feature and we can adjust it based on what feels right. I kept it at ‘20’ the whole time as reducing it any further started to introduce audio choppiness and that is just not good “stream content”. It was fine for the first two streams, but towards the middle of our third night of playing the game, it reared its ugly head. The game wanted us to walk in-step to get to the other side and failing to do so would result in us having to circle back to where we began on the screen. Walking into this square without care will lead to you falling into a pit and having to come around back. You can see Aetyate falling into a pit on the bottom-right with myself and authorblues right — tinahacks is presently dashing across on the far right. Typically if you run across a pit in a Zelda game, you can use your “Pegasus Boots” item to quickly dart across large gaps. However, the game developers placed what appears to be potato-pineapple hybrids in the way so if you were to dash across, you’d collide with them and then fall down the pit. The game requires you to walk parallel to each other in formation in order to keep the platform balanced and then upon approaching the blocked items, simultaneously pull them off of the ground and then toss them. If you can pull off the second part successfully, then the pit is resolved so all we need to worry about is just getting at least one of us across. With the current buffer settings, we probably made a dozen and a half if not more attempts. It was starting to look dire as the input latency combined with the latency that a Discord audio call produces made it impossible for us to just get the timing down right. It was beginning to look like this might be the end of this fun experiment until we tried one idea. Let’s just make the buffer not exist and play the game frame-by-frame. You absolutely should watch the video in this tweet to understand how everything went because while we were successful, someone decided to be a “bother” once it was known that we made it. Each frame we progressed was progress in itself and when we made it to the other side, almost all of us managed to remember to pick up the object on the other end — I inadvertently hit my sword button instead (oops). What proceeded was pure comedy because once one of us successfully got over, another went and attempted to sabotage everything because it was possible to get away with that now and I found myself and that saboteur at the bottom of the pit. However, this was no longer a problem as now the boots I had put on earlier were now possible as an option across this pit. At least two of us were on the other side despite someone’s best efforts. This wasn’t the only obvious latency problem we had to contend with as a prior boss battle during this stream was proving difficult due to a need to time certain actions, but this was the first time we had to adjust the emulation in order to actually make any meaningful progress. What’s next? We have a few more streams of this game left with plans for this upcoming Sunday and Tuesday (February 6 and 8, 2022), with the second day being a hopeful completion of what has been a rather fun experience. This will be on authorblues’ Twitch channel. If you’re interested in watching the past broadcasts, you can view the VODs on Twitch here (I will do my best to update this with the other streams once we are done): February 1, 2022 (Part 3) January 25, 2022 (Part 2) January 20, 2022 (Part 1) After completing our misadventures, we intend to play Final Fantasy Crystal Chronicles, which is another game I have never played. This is likely to be after the upcoming Frost Fatales 2022, an all-women speedrunning marathon I contribute my spare time to. I hope you’ll check out as we’re raising money for Malala Fund and lots of talented women will show how fast they can play games!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">More hacking on automating Wordle</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/01/30/more-hacking-on-automating-wordle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More hacking on automating Wordle" />
      
      <published>2022-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/01/30/more-hacking-on-automating-wordle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://cariad.keigher.ca/2022/01/30/more-hacking-on-automating-wordle/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just a warning: if you are playing Wordle and don’t want any hints, this is not the Medium entry for you. Also, I am not a mathematician or statistician, so everything is just based on my knowledge of cryptanalysis and nothing more.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One other thing to note is that the word list I am working with is not Wordle’s as I intentionally wanted to avoid looking at its source code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. So I had one remaining question from &lt;a href=&quot;https://katelibc.medium.com/hacking-wordle-through-automation-and-cryptanalysis-85b438328936&quot;&gt;my last entry on Wordle&lt;/a&gt;: what is the most efficient starting word overall?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Cares” has a word score of 967.4, whereas “audio” gets 288.4 and “ports” has 796.6. The point of the game is to produce an answer in as few steps as possible and while you will knock off a lot of vowels and consonants with those two, you are likely reducing the chances of answering in the fewest attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My choice of word also includes the letter “e”, which is the most common letter used in the English language. On average, you should see that letter appear about 10–13% of the time, with the letter “a” being about 7–9%, and “s” being 6–9%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can also order it as “scare” or “races” too if you desire, but I believe that with “s” at the end and putting “r” in the middle, you cover all initial possibilities quite effectively here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not like what I wrote here, but at the time I didn’t really run numbers on outcomes. However, I was working on this because you cannot really automate Wordle without a good starting word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the same logic from before, the process to find the winning word was fairly simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each starting word, we then ran through each possible five letter word other than itself. It would run each guess against an implementation of Wordle in my own code with the same hints and correct guesses. Once it got to an answer, it would then record all attempts into a set and then move on to the next word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/10sPLTqitT_TdO16_lziu1A_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word “bases” was guessed with a starting word of “caves” and made five other guesses before coming to an eventual answer. This obviously would have failed if I used it against Wordle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Wordle, there was no guess limit as I wanted to know how many attempts it would take using the methodology I did before where I came up with a list based on efficiency. So the first word based on possibilities made by the hints and correct letter guesses available from the list was the word chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are flaws with this list sorting as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/authorblues/status/1481292670769192962&quot;&gt;discussed on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted to stick to my current methodology, so we’ll proceed forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The worst words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining the worst word can be achieved one of two ways. We can either look for a group of words or a single word that has the most guess attempts or we can look at them on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minimum of the number of guesses is quite simple: one if you’re lucky, but if the word doesn’t match, then two. Guessing what the largest number of guesses will be took a little bit of magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words that managed to hit a the maximum-seen attempts of 14 were: “agile”, “anile”, “dells”, “duels”, “dulls”, “dully”, “exile”, “gaily”, “guile”, “gulls”, “gully”, “jails”, “jello”, “jells”, “jelly”, “jinns”, “jolly”, “keels”, “kelly”, “lolls”, “lolly”, “lulls”, “nails”, “ninny”, “nulls”, “quell”, “rails”, “rials”, “villa”, “ville”, “villi”, “yella”, “yells”, and “yield”. If you are to notice a pattern here, almost all of them have the letter ‘l’ in them, but this isn’t really the reason why they performed badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Word scores are all over the place with these words, which leads me to believe that it is not necessarily indicative of a good start. For example, “quells” is amongst that list and had a score of 307.4, but then “rails” received 768.6. The average score for all of the words was 531.1, so I’m not confident all that much in using that as a metric for a good starting word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then what about averages? This gives us a better picture because Wordle limits us to six guesses. I would suggest if a word has a minimum average of 4 or higher that it should not be used at the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst performing word had an average of 4.26 attempts, which was “jujus”. This was followed by “wheee” at 4.23, and “yukky” at 4.21. There were three tied for 4.2, and they were “vexes”, “sexes”, and “esses”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word score “jujus” was 506.6, but interestingly, “sexes” received 888.6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Is there a guaranteed winner?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer is: no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All words with this methodology ranged from 8 to 14 maximum attempts. No single word went below 8 attempts, meaning there are starting words which will lead to failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a silver-lining, the number of words with the smallest maximum is only slightly larger than the number of words with the largest maximum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 1,764 words of which had 12 maximum attempts, 2,085 with 11, 984 with 10, and 411 with 9. However, with 8, there are only 39 words, and all of them might justifiably be the best candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words that performed the best were “blest”, “deism”, “doest”, “durst”, “feist”, “heist”, “least”, “liest”, “merse”, “midst”, “obese”, “pseud”, “sebum”, “sedan”, “sedge”, “sedgy”, “sedum”, “seize”, “sepia”, “serge”, “serif”, “serum”, “sheaf”, “sheik”, “sherd”, “siege”, “sieve”, “skein”, “skirt”, “slept”, “speck”, “spend”, “sperm”, “steal”, “suede”, “swell”, “swift”, “welsh”, and “wrist”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1Ka5sISDp-NUVVWlfsGT_8A_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Obese” has a word score of 277.8 and “pseud” is 281.6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to word scores, we arrive upon something curious: the range of scores is between 277.8 and 526, with the average being 398.4. Perhaps the way to look at the word score is not at whether it is strong at the start, but instead if it eliminates all of the least likely? This would suggest that words such as “obese” or “pseud” could be good starting candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Could we find a most-likely?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I want to deviate: a maximum does not imply that it is the worst choice. And in this case, I am willing to believe this because I did find something amongst all of the words that allows me to suggest that there is either a flaw in my methodology or I am looking at this all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words “estop”, “epsom”, and “serum” had an average attempt count of 2.74, 2.77, and 2.79 each respectively. When I looked at their word scores, “estop” had 160.4, “epsom” had 165.8, and “serum” had 418.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to look at all words of which were lower than 2.9, and within the the 54 words, the minimum score was 106.6 and the maximum was 496, with an average of 336.3. I think I know where the word score’s usefulness may lie: it’s better to start with a lower than a higher one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I spoke about maximums earlier, “estop” found itself with a maximum of 9 attempts. In fact, “serum”, which had a slightly higher average than “estop” found itself with a maximum of 8 — “epsom” received 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is still an incorrect approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re looking at the average and what I’d like to know is what has the highest percentage of wins within the limitations imposed by the game. We have six guesses, so what word is best suited on average to produce an outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these parameters in mind, we can then use the following methodology: which word is most likely to get a guess correct within those six attempts and then not consider the steps beyond that point since they’re not indicative of what would be considered a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 5,756 words tested, one word managed to achieve a win in three moves 69.4% of the time: “verso”. It also achieved a win in two moves 10.8% of the time, four was 13.1%, five was 4.6%, and six was 1.5% — a 99.4% successful starting word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not the best word even though it is the best word for the quickest win — fortunately we already know the best one to use in order to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, “estop” had an average of 2.74 attempts before a win, but importantly it has the highest success rate. It edged out “verso” by achieving a 99.6% win rate with 46% of all attempts being achieved in its first two guesses and then three in 40% — four was 9.4%, five was 3.2%, and six was 0.9%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a failure on only 19 words from the word list — compared to 30 for the other word I was testing with — starting with just “estop” should net you a win most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in my opinion: “estop” is by far the best word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/1DezAoeADAebHml6mnxXMOA_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From January 30th’s Wordle: “estop” showed that despite failing the first two guesses, the algorithm did it in four tries whereas “verso” had to make an extra guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/KateLibC/WordleStats&quot;&gt;I’m happy to share the data I have made&lt;/a&gt; and I welcome you to demonstrate anything you have done with it. However, I must reiterate that I am not a statistician nor do I consider myself adept with mathematics. What I will say that I was out to have fun to solve this challenge and I feel like I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to play this game unconventionally and I think I accomplished that goal. There are some further ideas to achieve a 100% success rate or at least get extremely close to it, but being that I am at 99.6% successful on just this algorithm alone, it does make me think that this little project can be considered “ended”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Cariad Heather Keigher</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Just a warning: if you are playing Wordle and don’t want any hints, this is not the Medium entry for you. Also, I am not a mathematician or statistician, so everything is just based on my knowledge of cryptanalysis and nothing more. One other thing to note is that the word list I am working with is not Wordle’s as I intentionally wanted to avoid looking at its source code. Okay. So I had one remaining question from my last entry on Wordle: what is the most efficient starting word overall? “Cares” has a word score of 967.4, whereas “audio” gets 288.4 and “ports” has 796.6. The point of the game is to produce an answer in as few steps as possible and while you will knock off a lot of vowels and consonants with those two, you are likely reducing the chances of answering in the fewest attempts. My choice of word also includes the letter “e”, which is the most common letter used in the English language. On average, you should see that letter appear about 10–13% of the time, with the letter “a” being about 7–9%, and “s” being 6–9%. You can also order it as “scare” or “races” too if you desire, but I believe that with “s” at the end and putting “r” in the middle, you cover all initial possibilities quite effectively here. I did not like what I wrote here, but at the time I didn’t really run numbers on outcomes. However, I was working on this because you cannot really automate Wordle without a good starting word. Methodology Using the same logic from before, the process to find the winning word was fairly simple. For each starting word, we then ran through each possible five letter word other than itself. It would run each guess against an implementation of Wordle in my own code with the same hints and correct guesses. Once it got to an answer, it would then record all attempts into a set and then move on to the next word. The word “bases” was guessed with a starting word of “caves” and made five other guesses before coming to an eventual answer. This obviously would have failed if I used it against Wordle. Unlike Wordle, there was no guess limit as I wanted to know how many attempts it would take using the methodology I did before where I came up with a list based on efficiency. So the first word based on possibilities made by the hints and correct letter guesses available from the list was the word chosen. There are flaws with this list sorting as discussed on Twitter, but I wanted to stick to my current methodology, so we’ll proceed forward. The worst words Defining the worst word can be achieved one of two ways. We can either look for a group of words or a single word that has the most guess attempts or we can look at them on average. A minimum of the number of guesses is quite simple: one if you’re lucky, but if the word doesn’t match, then two. Guessing what the largest number of guesses will be took a little bit of magic. The words that managed to hit a the maximum-seen attempts of 14 were: “agile”, “anile”, “dells”, “duels”, “dulls”, “dully”, “exile”, “gaily”, “guile”, “gulls”, “gully”, “jails”, “jello”, “jells”, “jelly”, “jinns”, “jolly”, “keels”, “kelly”, “lolls”, “lolly”, “lulls”, “nails”, “ninny”, “nulls”, “quell”, “rails”, “rials”, “villa”, “ville”, “villi”, “yella”, “yells”, and “yield”. If you are to notice a pattern here, almost all of them have the letter ‘l’ in them, but this isn’t really the reason why they performed badly. Word scores are all over the place with these words, which leads me to believe that it is not necessarily indicative of a good start. For example, “quells” is amongst that list and had a score of 307.4, but then “rails” received 768.6. The average score for all of the words was 531.1, so I’m not confident all that much in using that as a metric for a good starting word. So then what about averages? This gives us a better picture because Wordle limits us to six guesses. I would suggest if a word has a minimum average of 4 or higher that it should not be used at the start. The worst performing word had an average of 4.26 attempts, which was “jujus”. This was followed by “wheee” at 4.23, and “yukky” at 4.21. There were three tied for 4.2, and they were “vexes”, “sexes”, and “esses”. The word score “jujus” was 506.6, but interestingly, “sexes” received 888.6. Is there a guaranteed winner? The short answer is: no. All words with this methodology ranged from 8 to 14 maximum attempts. No single word went below 8 attempts, meaning there are starting words which will lead to failure. There is a silver-lining, the number of words with the smallest maximum is only slightly larger than the number of words with the largest maximum. There are 1,764 words of which had 12 maximum attempts, 2,085 with 11, 984 with 10, and 411 with 9. However, with 8, there are only 39 words, and all of them might justifiably be the best candidates. The words that performed the best were “blest”, “deism”, “doest”, “durst”, “feist”, “heist”, “least”, “liest”, “merse”, “midst”, “obese”, “pseud”, “sebum”, “sedan”, “sedge”, “sedgy”, “sedum”, “seize”, “sepia”, “serge”, “serif”, “serum”, “sheaf”, “sheik”, “sherd”, “siege”, “sieve”, “skein”, “skirt”, “slept”, “speck”, “spend”, “sperm”, “steal”, “suede”, “swell”, “swift”, “welsh”, and “wrist”. “Obese” has a word score of 277.8 and “pseud” is 281.6. Going back to word scores, we arrive upon something curious: the range of scores is between 277.8 and 526, with the average being 398.4. Perhaps the way to look at the word score is not at whether it is strong at the start, but instead if it eliminates all of the least likely? This would suggest that words such as “obese” or “pseud” could be good starting candidates. Could we find a most-likely? This is where I want to deviate: a maximum does not imply that it is the worst choice. And in this case, I am willing to believe this because I did find something amongst all of the words that allows me to suggest that there is either a flaw in my methodology or I am looking at this all wrong. The words “estop”, “epsom”, and “serum” had an average attempt count of 2.74, 2.77, and 2.79 each respectively. When I looked at their word scores, “estop” had 160.4, “epsom” had 165.8, and “serum” had 418. I decided to look at all words of which were lower than 2.9, and within the the 54 words, the minimum score was 106.6 and the maximum was 496, with an average of 336.3. I think I know where the word score’s usefulness may lie: it’s better to start with a lower than a higher one. When I spoke about maximums earlier, “estop” found itself with a maximum of 9 attempts. In fact, “serum”, which had a slightly higher average than “estop” found itself with a maximum of 8 — “epsom” received 9. But this is still an incorrect approach. We’re looking at the average and what I’d like to know is what has the highest percentage of wins within the limitations imposed by the game. We have six guesses, so what word is best suited on average to produce an outcome. With these parameters in mind, we can then use the following methodology: which word is most likely to get a guess correct within those six attempts and then not consider the steps beyond that point since they’re not indicative of what would be considered a success. Of the 5,756 words tested, one word managed to achieve a win in three moves 69.4% of the time: “verso”. It also achieved a win in two moves 10.8% of the time, four was 13.1%, five was 4.6%, and six was 1.5% — a 99.4% successful starting word. But this is not the best word even though it is the best word for the quickest win — fortunately we already know the best one to use in order to win. As mentioned before, “estop” had an average of 2.74 attempts before a win, but importantly it has the highest success rate. It edged out “verso” by achieving a 99.6% win rate with 46% of all attempts being achieved in its first two guesses and then three in 40% — four was 9.4%, five was 3.2%, and six was 0.9%. With a failure on only 19 words from the word list — compared to 30 for the other word I was testing with — starting with just “estop” should net you a win most of the time. So in my opinion: “estop” is by far the best word. From January 30th’s Wordle: “estop” showed that despite failing the first two guesses, the algorithm did it in four tries whereas “verso” had to make an extra guess. The data I’m happy to share the data I have made and I welcome you to demonstrate anything you have done with it. However, I must reiterate that I am not a statistician nor do I consider myself adept with mathematics. What I will say that I was out to have fun to solve this challenge and I feel like I have. I wanted to play this game unconventionally and I think I accomplished that goal. There are some further ideas to achieve a 100% success rate or at least get extremely close to it, but being that I am at 99.6% successful on just this algorithm alone, it does make me think that this little project can be considered “ended”.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
</feed>
